<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The agrement of the holye fathers, and doctors of the churche, vpon the cheifest articles of Christian religion as appeareth on the nexte syde folowinge, very necessary for all curates. Gathered together by Iohn Aungell preist, one of the Quenes maiesties chapleyns.</title>
            <author>Angel, John, fl. 1555.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 116 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 634</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108528</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844186</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844186</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8976</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69179)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8976)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 165:20, 307:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The agrement of the holye fathers, and doctors of the churche, vpon the cheifest articles of Christian religion as appeareth on the nexte syde folowinge, very necessary for all curates. Gathered together by Iohn Aungell preist, one of the Quenes maiesties chapleyns.</title>
                  <author>Angel, John, fl. 1555.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], cviii, [2] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By William Harford, for William Seres. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at Lo[n]don in Aldersgate strete :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1555?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 958.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 958 on UMI microfilm reel 307.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in Bodleian Library and the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 165 £ (Bodleian Library copy) and at reel 307 #1 (British Library copy, identified as STC 958).</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Cum priuilegis imprimendum solum.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Thirty-nine Articles --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:1"/>
            <p>The agrement of the holye Fathers, and Doctors of the churche, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the cheifeſt articles of Chriſtian religion, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth on the nexte ſyde folowinge, very neceſſary for all curates. Gathered together by Iohn Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell preiſt, one of the Quenes maieſties Chapleyns.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:2"/>
            <head>¶ The contentes of the boke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>i. Of the holy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed Sacramente of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloud of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>ii. Of the ſigne of the croſſe.</item>
               <item>iii. Of prayinge for the deade.</item>
               <item>iiii. Of penaunce, confeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion, and ſatiſfaction.</item>
               <item>v. Of praying to ſaints</item>
               <item>vi. Of the counſels, and auctorities of the fathers.</item>
               <item>vii. Againſt the mariage of preiſtes.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the mooſt excellente and vertuous Princeſſes Quene Marye, wyfe to oure mooſte ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raynge Lorde, Philip by the grace of God. &amp;c. Iohn Aungell, one of youre graces chaplyns of youre honourable Chappel, wiſſheth perpetuall felicitie, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this worlde, but alſo in the worlde to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Monge the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites whiche we haue recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye God (mooſt worthy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellente Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe) there is none in mine opinion for the whiche we are more bounde vnto his mercifull goodnes, then for that it hath moued hym of his
<pb facs="tcp:8976:3"/> gentle benignite, to call vnto vs agayne his trewe religion, whiche our forefathers hath kept from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginninge. For who knoweth not that this noble realme of England hath ben ſeduced euen now of late dayes, thorough ignoraunce, naye, naye, rather thorough ſtubbernes, and for lacke of grace. For they knowinge him as God, honoured hym not as God: but thinking the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues wiſe, became fooles. Who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſymple people, percea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth not what intollerable abuſes haue ben (vnder pretence of true relygion and godlynes) vſed and maynteyned in this churche of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande? As falſe interpretinge of Scriptures, vtterly denying of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy doctours and fathers of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes churche, but only ſuch as made for their purpoſe. Tyll ſuche tyme that it pleaſed hym of his infinite
<pb facs="tcp:8976:3"/> mercy, to ſende vs a newe Iudith, by whoſe godlines the trewe light and knowledge of Goddes worde is nowe by her broughte agayne, whiche frome the death of that no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble prince her father Henry y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. viii. was here in this realme extuncte, and vtterly aboliſhed, to the vtter vndoyng of mens conſcience: but now thankes be to God the father of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to ſpringe and ſhyne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. This noble Iudith is oure mooſt ſoueraygne Ladye Quene Mary, a Princeſſe garniſhed with ſo many excellent giftes of grace, vertue, nature, and fortune, that ſhe is in verye dede, (and therefore moſt worthely called) the perfecte mirroure, and pearle of al Chriſten Princeſſe. To wade her in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayſe of her Princely qualities, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble actes, it is not my purpoſe, for
<pb facs="tcp:8976:4"/> that I know it to be an enterpriſe farre excedinge the compaſſe of my ſymple wyt and vnderſtandynge. But onely to declare howe muche we are bounde, cheifly vnto God, and next vnto her mooſt excellente highnes, that we haue nowe oure olde and true religion broughte home agayne: and are cured again through God by her, of oure olde blyndenes that we were in, by the medecyne of veritie. For we nowe hauynge agayne the true knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, whiche oure forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hath lefte behynde them by wrytinge, we begynne agayne to ſe and perfectly to knowe Chriſte to be in the Sacrament of the aulter, whome to knowe perfectly, is euer laſtynge lyfe and ſaluation. But ſo longe as the ſayde Scriptures were falſely interpreted, by Sedici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and falſe preachers, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true
<pb facs="tcp:8976:4"/> knowledge of Scripture kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the people, fewe or none knewe Chriſt aryght: and none leſſe then they, who toke vpon them to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cheif profeſſours, and ſetters forth of Chriſtes religion. For what els is it knowe Chriſt, but to beleue his worde? Who ſheweth me which is his word, but the catholike chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. For S. Auguſtyne ſayeth: I wold neuer haue beleued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel but by the churche. So that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth therby, howe greatly they are deceaued, that wyll take vpon them to denye the olde fathers of Chriſtes churche, to maynetayne their vnthrifty purpoſes: yea, and not onely thoſe: but alſo certayne places of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bible that maketh not for them. For ſurely it is the holye fathers that ſheweth and expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnto vs playnely the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which nowe of late hath ben
<pb facs="tcp:8976:5"/> in controuerſy, not with good men, (but with thoſe that be of the euyl ſort, as hereafter ſhal folow) whoſe iudgementes be verye godlye.</p>
            <p>Teachinge vs truely to knowe by fayth, howe that the body of Chriſt is in the Sacrament of the aulter: becauſe his wordes doth ſo euident<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly declare the ſame, ſayinge: <hi>This is my body.</hi> And foraſmuche as theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye fathers hereafter folowynge, hath left theyr myndes in wryting (as concernyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes reall body, to be in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the aulter, and not only of this, but of certaine other matters whiche hath ben in queſtion) vnto all people that wyll be ſaued, none excepte. For nowe (thankes be to God) I truſt that Idolatry, hypocriſye, and all vngodlynes, is cleane plucked vp by the rootes: and that the trewe religion of God
<pb facs="tcp:8976:5"/> hath taken his place agayne. Now is falſe doctrine exiled, and Gods worde truely preached &amp; ſet forth. Nowe is that abhomination and deſolation pluckte downe: and the true worſhyppyng of Chriſt in the Sacrament ſet vp agayne. Nowe I truſt in almighty God, that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande hath forſaken all theyr ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable preachers and teachers agaynſt the preſence of Chriſt to be in the Sacramente of the aulter, with al theyr vngodly deuiſes, and deuelyſh inuencions. For if that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> (O Englande) had that grace geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the of God, that thou woldeſt call vnto thy remembraunce, howe that this Iudith, at the riſynge of our Holifernus, had the hartes of men, and not the bodyes: And that at the riſynge, and proceding forth of that peſtiferous traytor Wyat, had the bodyes and not the hartes
<pb facs="tcp:8976:6"/> and yet ouercame her enemies by the power of God, it were ſuche a miracle vnto the, whereby to cauſe the to forſake all thy noughty opi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nions and errours. But yet this y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> muſt thinke that it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth by the mere mercy &amp; goodnes of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God towardes vs, and not of our deſeruinges: who hath raiſed vp vnto vs, now in theſe our lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes, this noble Iudith, a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of mooſt excellente giftes, and ſinguler qualities, whollye geuen to the ſtudy of vertue &amp; godlines. Wherfore all Englande hath iuſte occaſion to reioyce at this youre graces doinges, in that ye be ſo ſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dious to call vs home agayne (like loſt ſhepe that hath runne aſtray) to our olde and true religion, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che our olde fathers hath left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hynde them from tyme to tyme: be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſechinge almightye God therin to
<pb facs="tcp:8976:6"/> be your ſtrength, ſhielde and buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. Moſt humbly beſeching youre grace (moſt gratious Lady) in good paſt to take this my good zele and diligence. And in caſe any thinge ſhall not ſufficiently aunſwer your graces mynde, or deſire, the ſame to impute rather to the lacke of facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and knowledge, then to any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faute of good wyll in me. I ſhall here without any farther circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of wordes, commende, and leaue this ſmall worke to the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent reading, and folowinge of all true Chriſten people. And with mooſt harty prayer, beſeche almigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye God longe yeares to proſper and continewe the proſperouſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of youre hyghneſſe, to thende that by youre good helpe and meanes, the deuoute people of this youre realme, maye receaue
<pb facs="tcp:8976:7"/> this whiche is Gods procedynges, and your graces gentle embracin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, to theyr continuall helth, and comforte both of body and ſoule, to the wyll of GOD, thorowe Ieſus Chriſt oure Lorde: To whom with the father, and the ſonne, and the holye gooſt, be all laude, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and glory, both in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="quotation">
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:7"/>
            <head>¶ Anacletus byſhop and Martyr, in his firſte Epiſtle written to all congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od ſacrificers, his diuine myniſters, ought not in any wiſe to be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, but to be mayntayned, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden and ſupported of euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Goddes ſacrificers, trewly while they execute that office, ought not alone to be withoute wytnes of trew and iuſt performance of their deutie. But being occupyed in this holy action, to haue aſſiſtens, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adiutors, and hearers: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Dd"/> To the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent they maye be proued and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to haue perfectly ſacrificed, for the auctorite of the deuyne lawes approueth this Deut. xii. in theſe words. Se thou offer not thy ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb facs="tcp:8976:8"/> to thy lorde god promyſcually in euerye place: but in that place whiche the Lorde hathe choſen. A Byſhoppe ſacrynge at the aulter, let hym haue witneſſe with hym, (as I haue ſayde before) yea, and more then any other preiſt. For as he ſitteth on the higher pynacle of honor: ſo it is behouable at his my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſtrynge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there be preſent grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nombre of recordes, vpon more ſolempne dayes. A Biſhop ſhoulde haue ſeuen, fyue, or thre Deacons at the leaſt, whiche be called his eyes, with ſubdeacons, and other miniſters, who clothed in holy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelmentes, before and behynde, with preiſtes on euerye ſyde, dyrectly of the right agaynſt the lefte, Contrite in harte, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in ſpryt. Standing alſo with vpright faces to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauenwardes, ſhall kepe hym frome all violence
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:8976:8"/> and vylanye. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Bb"/> And be preſt with conſent and ſaruice to further the ſacrifice. The ſacringe fynyſſhed, let them all communicate whiche be entred within the bondes of the churche degrees. For ſuch was bothe the Apoſtells origynall ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, as is the Churche cuſtome. And in his ſeconde Epyſtle of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyon of Archebyſhoppes. The accuſacion of byſhoppes and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſts, agaynſt the which matter you haue conſulted with vs, ought not to be effecteous, but at their han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des who be fytte, good and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men, voyde frome affections, crymes and ſuſpicyons. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord will not the holy handelers of hys bodye to be dyffamed of vnworthy perſones, nor he hath geuen leue to bakbyte any of them. For he him ſelfe with his owne bodely handes whipped the vnpreiſtly preiſts out
<pb facs="tcp:8976:9"/> of the churche.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>Saynte Clement martyr, the thirde from Peter.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Dd"/> CLement byſhoppe in his fyrſt booke of reknowlegementes, to Iames y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes brother, bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in S. Peter thus ſpeakinge. In concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I warned them that before we went forwardes to prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che among al people y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trew know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of god the Father, that they ſhoulde be reconcylyd frome ſynne to God, receauinge his ſonne. For other wayes is ther none, to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon, or of declaringe oure good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace graunted and inſpyred by the holy goſte. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Cc"/> They dyd haſt to be waſhed in the bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſme of the thre folde inuocation, but they dyd take the body of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt: who onely
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:8976:9"/> ought to be beleued eneſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things he hath taught. And in his ſecond Epyſtle to Iames y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, entyteled: <hi>de ſacris, uaſis, &amp; ueſtibus.</hi> Byſhop Clement to his derely beloued Iames, Byſhop of Ieruſalem. Foraſmoche as we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſo receaued, and be ſo taught by ſaynt Peter, the Father of all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtels, who toke the keyes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, how we ſhoulde vſe the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and what we ſholde iudge and defende of them, which are exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy places, it is ſemyng that I inſtructe you of the ordre of the ſame. The ſacraments of the diuine ſecrets, are commytted to thre degrees: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye: a preſt, a deacon, and a ſubdeacon, who with feare and trymblyng of god, ought to gather or kepe together y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lordes bodye: Leaſt any corrupcion be founde or ſtycke
<pb facs="tcp:8976:10"/> in the place wher the hooſts ought to be kept, leſte when it is negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently layde vp, the body of oure Lorde ſhoulde be moche indama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. For the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the body of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, yf it be neglygently delte, and the preaſt do not regarde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> admonyſhments of lower offycers, let hym be ſtry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with ſome greuous ſequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion, and humbled or ponyſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a plage. Certes, let ſo greate and large ſacrifice be offered in the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in quantytie, as be ſuffycient for the rated nombre of people: yf there be any ſurpluſe remayninge after the dyſtrybucyon, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be reſerued vntyll the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng. But lowly and dreadefully let the clerkes receaue them. And they which do conſume the reſidue of the Lordes bodye being lefte in the place of reſeruacion: let them
<pb n="iiii" facs="tcp:8976:10"/> not by and by go to gether, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaye or fyl them ſelues with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meates,<note place="margin">&amp;</note> leſt they entermyngle other victuall, to the holy porcyon which ought fyrſt by degeſtyon to be conuayde into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> innermoſt and entier parts. Therfore if they take repaſt of the Lordes bodye, let the miniſters which haue ſo done in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morowe earely, faſt vntyl the ſyxe houre. And yf they haue eaten the Lordes porcyon at the thyrde or fourth houre: let them abſtayne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meate tyll nyght, thus by ſecrete ſanctyfycation y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euerlaſtynge ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes are to be kept. And it to loweth: for the buſines of the Lord ought not to be ſlackly accomplyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Agayne, and agayne, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, and commaunde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes &amp; remanents of the body of our Lord, &amp; the Chalice ordeyned for the veſſel of our Lordes bloud,
<pb facs="tcp:8976:11"/> let it be warely and dilyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pared by the myniſter: leſt it ſcars clene waſhed by the deacon, maye turne hym to treſpas in offeringe. Thus w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al honeſtye ſuch thinges as we haue before ſpoken of, muſt be fulfilled. And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrd Epiſtle to the ſame entent (of the office of preiſtes and clerks) <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Dd"/> Therfore it is behouable to vs here, ronnnig the rayce of this ſhorte lyfe, in this va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yle of myſery, to perceaue, acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege, and wholy to confyrme vs to the will of almighty God, where we ought, &amp; what place is appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> celebracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſacrifices. For it is not lawfull to do maſſe or any ſacrifyce in any place, but in ordynary places, commaunded and alowed by youre owne byſhoppe, And conſecrated by the cheif eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall power in our dyoces. For otherwiſe, theſe holy things or deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:8976:11"/> be not to be admyniſtred in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcripture, both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new &amp; tholde teſtamente inſtructynge vs. This aſſertyon the Apoſtles haue recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and lerned of our Lorde: And this haue they delyuered &amp; taught vs. And theſe thinges we teache, &amp; I ioyne you all which haue in hand any ſpiritual charge, to holde, vſe, kepe, and execute the ſame, with oute any repyne or reprehenſion. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Ee"/> Here after foloweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> order of the wordes which Saynt Clement v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in ſaying maſſe after this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. We deſyre the O Lorde, that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wilte ſend thy holy ſprite vpon this ſacrifyce, whiche maye make this breade the body of thy Chriſt, and that which is in the cuppe the blode of thy Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:12"/>
            <head>¶ S. Denyſe the Arapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyte whom Paule makyth menci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of in the Actes of thappoſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les .xvii. Chapter, and was his diſciple.</head>
            <p>SAynte Denyſe one of the nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the ſeuere Iudges of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens conuerted by Saynt Paule. And by Saynte Clement, with theſe holy men Ruſticus and Elu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therius ſent into Fraunce: In the thyrde parte of the ſeconde Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter entreatynge of Eccleſiaſticall gouernaunce. In the laſt ende of al thinges dew to be done in perfight baptyſinge. The biſhop calleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptyzed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt holy Euchariſt, and geueth vnto them the Godly communion of the chefe and moſte ſouerayne ſacrament of the body &amp; blode of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt. And in the fyrſt part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .iii. chap.
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:8976:12"/> Nor it is almoſte Godly or right any deutye belongynge a preiſtes office to be executed, oneles he acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pliſhe this diuine and moſte riall ſacrament of Euchariſte. And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeconde parte of the ſayde chapter. And the principalles of the ſame order together with the preiſtes do put vppon the aulter the holye bread, &amp; the chalyce of benedictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: when there hathe gone before an vniuerſall prayſe, and confeſſion of the hole quere. That done the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerente prelate makinge an holy prayer, doth ſhew holy peace to all the congregacyon. And when they haue one another ſaluted, the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall rehereſall of holye thinges is made. And when the prelate and other preiſtes haue waſhed their handes, the Byſhoppe ſtandeth at the myddes of the aulter.</p>
            <p>All the onelye electe and choſen
<pb facs="tcp:8976:13"/> preiſtes that ſhall receaue, taken oute of the nombre of the myni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters do ſtande aboute. But the byſhoppe as ſone as he hath pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and extolled the Godly gyftes: maketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy and high miſteries, and ſheweth openly thoſe thinges whiche he hath extolled, before hyd and couered with reuerent tokens. And holdinge in ſight reuerently the Godly rewardes, he hym ſelfe is turned to the holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the Lordes maundeth: and dothe exhort the people to take parte. At the laſt communion receaued and geuen to all that come to receaue it, he geueth thankes and fynyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myſterys. And in the third parte of the ſame Chapiter, in this maner trulye whan that the laſt &amp; moſte excellent bounty of God is prayſed &amp; magnified: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuine drink and cuppe of bleſſynge is handled
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:8976:13"/> &amp; propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Aa"/> And it foloweth: but marke this alſo, that the reuerent tokens being ſet vpon the aulter, by the which Chriſt is betokened &amp; taken: and by &amp; by without delay, the deſcription of ſayntes is there preſent, declaringe their inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble coniunctions, and moſte holye and high vnyon with Chriſte. And it foloweth: wherefore reuerently, &amp; of his Byſhoply office, after his holy prayſe of the diuine workes, he humbly excuſethe hym ſelfe, for that he offeryth and ſacrifyſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> helthfull hooſt whiche is ouer hym, cryinge vnto hym comely at fyrſte, ſayinge. Thou haſt ſayd: do this in remembraunce of me. Then thus great a myſterye being of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ymytation of hym ſelfe, he doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire and praye to be made a ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blable to Chriſt as frayle ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he maye bothe make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrament
<pb facs="tcp:8976:14"/> worthely, and purely diſtribute it. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they, who be aboute to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy communion, may wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thely take parte with hym. And ſo he myniſtreth the moſte reuerente myſtery, and ſetteth them in ſight propounded holilye vnder ſignes. Either elſe he openeth, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth the couert and vndeuyded breade, brekynge it in peces &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge one chalyce amonge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all, he dothe multyply ſhaply &amp; diſtri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnite of our Lordes blood, contayned within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde chalyce. Thus conſumyth the holy myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye. For that wyne ſymply and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of our Lorde by his dyuyne worde in his aſſumption of our humayne nature, hathe gone before and occupied place or he was entered that compound and viſible ſigne of his incomparable bownty &amp; power: wherein it is mercyfully
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:8976:14"/> made euident w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> how ſuer a knot of ſocyetye, he hath faſtened vs to hym, ioyninge his diuine excellent exiſtence to our earthy matters. Surely let vs agre with hym, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as members with the body, &amp; let vs be glued vnto hym by ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blablenes of clene &amp; godly lyuing. Leſt murdered w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vglye vyce, we may be made vnmete for the dyui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and moſte delicate members, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not able to ſtyck with him, but ſlydynge into co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynuance of nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghty lyfe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>The wordes of the holy man Marcial, which was ſent of ſaynt Peter to prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:15"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="N"/> 
               <hi>A</hi> Sacrifice is offered vpon an alter vnto God, not to man nor Angell. Nor that is not onely done vpon an alter halowed, but a clene ſacrifyce is offered vnto God in euery place as he dothe teſtifye, whoſe boody and blood we offer, to optayne euerlaſtynge lyfe. Truely euen the ſame offerynge which the Iewes made in deſpyte, wenynge to haue aboliſhed his name oute of the earthe, whiche we make in the conſecrate alter for our ſaluation, knowyng &amp; beleuing onely by this remedy, to attayne lyfe and eſcape death. For this the Lorde comma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unded vs to do in remembrance of hym.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Ignatius the diſciple of Saint Iohn the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt.</head>
            <pb n="ix" facs="tcp:8976:15"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="X"/> LEt the ſtable Euchariſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med affirmydly the bodye and bloode of Chriſt. And in his epiſtle that he writeth vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romayns, I deſyre ſaith he, the fode of God, the heauenly fode of lyfe, which is the fleſhe of Ieſu Chriſt, the ſonne of the lyuinge God, who was borne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt tyme, of the fead of Dauid &amp; Abraham, &amp; I deſyre for to drynk the bloode of hym who is loue with out corruption, and lyfe euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="X"/> They do not admyt the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, and oblations, bycauſe thei do not confeſſe the Euchariſt to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh of our Sauiour Ieſu chriſt which fleſh ſuffred for our ſynnes whiche fleſhe the father by his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitye hathe ſteryd vp.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>Saynt Alexander byſhop the Fyrſt martyr. C.xx.
<pb facs="tcp:8976:16"/> ¶ Alexanderin his Epiſtle to all churches.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> IN the oblation of Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes whiche be made ſolemply at maſſes the paſſion of our Lorde is to be mengled, to the intente that his paſſion may be celebrate, whoſe body and bloud is made, ſo that all wicked and ſuperſticious opynions abolyſhed, breade only and wyne myxte with water, maye be offered in the ſacrifyce, for ſynnes and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes therby are done awaye: with the whiche oblations the Lorde is contented and pleaſed, and will forgeue high and gretious offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, for what more myghty and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſacrifice maye be, then of the body and bloud of Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Saint Ireneus, Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carpus diſciple, in his .iiii. boke</head>
            <pb n="x" facs="tcp:8976:16"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> AGaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hereſyes of Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius and ſuche other. We offer thoſe thinges vnto hym whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che belongeth vnto hym, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge accordinglye the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and vnitie of fleſhe and ſprite, for lyke as the breade made of grayne taken frome the grounde, called by conſecration, is no more nowe commentable breade, but the bodye and bloude of Chriſte, ſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon .ii. thinges, an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and an heauenlye: euen ſo oure bodyes perceauing the ſacrament, be no more now corruptible, haui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hope of reſurrection. And i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his fyft boke agaynſt hereſyes. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> By what meanes therfore both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myxed cup and the frute of breade perceaueth the worde of God, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="X"/> is made the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt of the body and bloude of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:17"/>
            <p>For God in that he is God: hathe nether breth bones ne fleſhe. But ſpeakynge as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernynge that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and proportion whiche is like vnto man whiche ſtandeth compacte of fleſh, ſynowes, and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whiche is noriſhed with the cuppe, whiche is the bloode, and is enoreaſyd with the breade whiche is his body.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>Tertulyane in his boke of reſurrection of the fleſh.</head>
            <p>OVre fleſhe eateth the bodye &amp; bloode of Chriſt, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule alſo may be replenyſhed and fully fed with God.</p>
            <p>And in his boke of prayer he ſaith, bread is the worde of the lyuinge God, which came doune i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to his fote ſtole of the earth from his throne of heauen. Then his veraye bodye
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:8976:17"/> is demyd and thought to be in the ſimilitude of breade. Saynge: <hi>This is my body.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Ff"/> Therfore we clamynge &amp; requirynge our dayelye bread, do aſke a perpetuite, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynuaunce in Chriſt and an vnſeperable vnite with his body. Agaynſt Marcyon he ſaith: we do knowe, receaue and beleue all the goſpelles of Chriſt by the churche, and not otherwyſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>S. Cypryan martyr. ccxlix Cypryan Martyr in the fyrſte boke of his Epiſtelles in the ſeconde epiſtle.</head>
            <p>NOw not onely to the weake or ſycke but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> valyant peace is neceſſarye. Not only to perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes departyng, but to the liuinge communion ſhoulde be minyſtred, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> intent we maye not leaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> naked and weaponles, whome we
<pb facs="tcp:8976:18"/> exhort to battayle. But y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we maye defend them with the ſhelde of the bodye and bloude of Chriſt. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body &amp; bloud of Chriſt is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it maye be a ſauegarde to the receauers, and that we Arme them with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> armour of the Lordes health, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we wolde ſaue agaynſt our goſtely enemy. For why ſhould we teache, or moue them to ſpende their bloud in confeſſinge Chriſtes name, yf in this chiuallry we deny them the bloude of Chriſte? Or by what meanes do we make them fyt for the cup of martirdome, if we do not admyt them fyrſte to drynke of the chalice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De cena domini.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> Our Lorde maketh euen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally vntill this daye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:8976:18"/> this his moſte trew &amp; holy body, &amp; maketh it holy, bleſſeth it, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth it to them which deuoutely receaueth it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> THe breade which the Lorde gaue to his diſciples chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged not in forme, but in nature, and by the omnipotente power of the worde, is made fleſhe.</p>
               <p>And as in the perſonne of Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manhod was ſene and the Godhed hydde, ſo in the viſible ſacramente the diuine nature inuiſible, infun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth hym ſelfe, to the entent that aboute the ſacrament ſhoulde be deuotion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And in the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> This common bread chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged into fleſhe and bloude, procureth to bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes lyfe and increaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:8976:19"/>
               <head>Idem</head>
               <p>The high preſt bryngeth forth bread &amp; wyne, this is (ſaith he) my body, they eate and drynke of the ſame bread after a viſible forme: but afore theſe words, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> meat was common, only it was profitable for the body to be noriſhed, &amp; gaue help of a corporall lyfe. But from what tyme it was of the Lorde ſpoken, this do in remembraunce of me, it is fleſhe &amp; bloud. As often as with theſe wordes and this faithe it is done (that ſuperſubſtancial bread, and cup of benediction, ſolemplye conſecrate) it doth profight to life and health of the hole Man: Alſo being a medecyn &amp; brent offeringe to heale infirmyties, and pourge iniquities. That it was an other thinge, that fyrſt was ſette forth &amp; conſumed, and an other that was geuen of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſter and deſtributed,
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:8976:19"/> whan the falſe mynde of Iudas tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy meate. The holy ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed breade enteryd into the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mouthe, the murdering mynde not beynge able to ſuſteyne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght of ſo greate a ſacrament, was blowen away lyke chaffe frome the floure, and ran hedlynge to perditi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, to deſperation, and to the rope.</p>
               <p>The ſacrament, Chriſte ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme calleth it hys bodye, ſometyme his fleſhe and bloud, &amp; ſometime bread.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>Origen in his .v. Homilye. <hi>Domine non ſum dignus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHan ye receaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy meat and vncorrupted diſhe, thou doſt vſe the breade and the cup of lyfe, thou eateſt and drinkeſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloud of our Lorde, ther the Lorde entereſt into thy houſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Diſt. Viii</head>
               <p>The ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord dyd inſtitute
<pb facs="tcp:8976:20"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Q"/> when after the figuratyue lambe, he dyd reache his body to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples at ſupper.</p>
               <p>When theſe wordes be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſaith Origen) <hi>This is my body,</hi> and <hi>this is my bloud,</hi> ther is a certayne conuerſion made of breade and wyne into the ſubſtaunce of the bodye and bloude of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord Ieſus goynge to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inuiſible thinges of his Fathers mageſtie, the figuratyue paſchall beinge ſcelebrate with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſciples, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="y"/> wyllynge to commende vnto them a certayne memoryall vnder forme of breade and wyne, he dyd ſo geue his bodye and bloude to them, that he myght ſhew the ſacramentes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde law, amonge which the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice of the paſchal lambe was chefe to be ended in his death, &amp; the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new law to be inſtitute, in whiche the miſtery of Euchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia
<pb n="xiiii" facs="tcp:8976:20"/> excelleth.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>Chriſoſtem in his .lxxxiii. Homili. Vpon Saynt Math.</head>
            <p>LEt vs beleue God in euery thinge and not ſaye agaynſt hym,<note place="margin">Verba dei defrauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri non pu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</note> yea although the thing that he ſayth doth appere an inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence both to our ſences, thought, &amp; vnderſtandinge, and dothe alſo exceade our ſences, capacite, and reaſone. Let vs I beſeche you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue his wordes in al thinges, but chefly in the ſacrament, not onely vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe thinges, which lye before vs:<note place="margin">His wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des can no the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaued, our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eaſely be deceiued</note> but conſiderynge alſo his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. For by his wordes we can not be deceaued, His wordes can not be falſe, ourſences are moſt ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy to be dyſſayued. Wherfore ſeyng Chriſte hathe ſayde. <hi>This is my bodye,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:8976:21"/> let vs nothinge doute therof but beleue and perceaue it with the eyes of our vnderſtanding.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In his .iii. boke, <hi>Dialogorum, Cap. iiii.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Beholde the dignite of the preiſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hode whervpon we ſpeake, for it is done in earth, but his office is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in heuenly buſyneſſes. For conſequently, neither man, nor An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell,<note place="margin">Non homo non Ange<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lus, nec Archange<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lus hoc ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſtituit.</note> nor archangell, nor vertu, nor any other creature but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt hath inſtitute this office, and yet remayning in fleſhe, hath geuen to peruſe the minyſtery of angelles. For the which thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſhop muſt (as he that were in heuen, and wer mixed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertues) do this thing, ſo it is lightenyd with the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of lyfe. For when y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſeeſt oure Lord offered, and the preiſt ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding at the aulter with inſence, &amp; praing for hym ſelfe and for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, thou
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:8976:21"/> thinkeſt thou arte with men, and not ſtrayght way tranſlatyd into the heuenes: &amp; excludinge al ſence of the fleſhe oute of thy mynde, thou doeſt with naked ſoul, &amp; with moſt clere reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance, behold thoſe thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in heauenly places.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="G"/> O myracle, oh beneuolence of God in vs, that Chriſte ſytteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue at the righte hande of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and yet at the time of ſacrifice he is contayned in the handes of men, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> and is geuen vnto them that deſyer to taſte of hym, and to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braſed with worſhyppynge,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In his ſermon of Iudas the traiter.</head>
               <p>Where wilte thou y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we prepare the paſſeouer. Not that, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ours:<note place="margin">Sermons de Iude proditione</note> but in the meane ſeaſon he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtode the Iews paſſeouer. And the diſciples dyd prepare, but this that is ours, he hym ſelfe dyd ordayne,
<pb facs="tcp:8976:22"/> and not only ordayne, but he is it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> made it. Why dyd Chriſte eate it? yea, for he dyd fulfill al thinges thar were of the lawe. And bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes paſſed away by forgetti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefyttes of God, he with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebracion of the feſtiuitie dyd ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth memory vnto them of his be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefittes, and therfore dyd he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſeouer to be ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctified. And by that alſo was another greatter benefyt ſhewed, that that lambe was a figure of a lambe to come.<note place="margin">Agnus pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſchalis um<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bra. Chriſtus veritas. Super Epi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtolam ad Hebreos, Cap. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> And that bloude ſhewed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes bloud. That lambe was a ſhadow, this a verite. And therfore in it, both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſouer of the fygure &amp; verite is celebrat. Now therfore their ſwete breades be vnclene, their feſtiual dayes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lauful.<note place="margin">Quotidie offerendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="P"/> What do we? do not we offer euery day? we offer truly, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge remembrance of his deathe.
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:8976:22"/> And this ſacrifice is one,<note place="margin">Vna eſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia,</note> not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. For that was offered into the holy of the holynes, &amp; this ſacrifice is an enſample of that, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very ſame do we offer, and not now one lamb &amp; to morowe an other, but alway one. Therfore this ſacrifice is one,<note place="margin">Vbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Deus offertur.</note> elſe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reaſon, bycauſe it is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in many places, ther be many Chriſtes. No,<note place="margin">Commemo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ratio.</note> but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord is euery where one, and here beinge ful, and ther ful, one body, for as he that is offered euery where, is one bodye, and not many bodys, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo alſo is the ſacrifice one. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="P"/> He is our byſhop which offered the hooſt, makynge vs clean, and that ſame do we now offer,<note place="margin">Idem ſacri ſicium.</note> which then offered can not be conſumed, and that we do, is done in remembraunce of hym. None other ſacryfyce do we but alway the ſame. <hi>Super Math.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let all men beleue that euen now
<pb facs="tcp:8976:23"/> alſo is celebrate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper in which Chriſte hym ſelfe dyd ſit. For ther is no dyfference betwene that and this. For that is not made of man, &amp; this of hym. Therfore when thou ſeiſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſt geue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the body, thinke not that it is reached to the by the handes of the preſt, but by chriſtes. For as in baptiſme, thou art not baptiſed of the preſt, but of God: So hath not God to Aungelles commytted this office. But he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent byddeth and ſaieth: let vs here therfore as wel the preſtes as other. How greate, how merue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous a thynge is graunted to vs. Let vs here I praye you, &amp; be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayde of his fleſh geuen to vs, his owne fleſhe offered, hath he ſette forth to the Iewes euery year in re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membrance of his benefyttes.<note place="margin">Chriſtus quotidie nobis pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ponitur.</note> God hathe ſet forth holy dayes to the: daylye that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhouldeſt not forget,
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:8976:23"/> is he ſet forthe. For this is a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of peace. Let no Iudas, no Simon come to this thy table.</p>
               <p>The Iewes paſſouer was an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is voyd and paſt: but now is com vnto vs the ſpiritual paſſeouer, whiche Chriſt hym ſelfe made. For when they dyd eate and drinke, he toke breade and brake it, and ſayde: this is my body which ſhalbe geuen for you. They knowe what I ſpeake, which be conſecrate to deuine miſteris. And afterward he toke the cup and ſayde: this is my bloud which ſhalbe ſhed for you in remiſſion of ſynnes. And Iudas was ꝑſent, Chriſt ſaying theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, this is my bloud. Say Iudas, whom haſt thou ſold for .xxx. penſe. This is the ſame bloud of which thou madeſt a bargayne afore with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pharyſeys. Oh mercy of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Dementia Iude,</note> Oh madnes of Iudas. He made a
<pb facs="tcp:8976:24"/> bargyn to ſel Chriſt for .xxx. penſe. And Chriſt of his clemency offered to hym the ſame bloude that he had ſold, that he myght haue had remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſinnes, if he had not ben vnfaithful.<note place="margin">Remiſſio peccatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſanguine Chriſti</note> For he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the communicacion of that Sacrifice. And his fete alſo Chriſt dyd waſhe, as of the others, that he ſhold haue had none excuſe of his malice: But he being deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, thought the lyinges in waight of his mynde. But now, a conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient tyme doth inuite vs to the terrible table, and with a congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent watching. Let no Iudas be founde ther: Let no wycked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon come therto, nor none priked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> poyſon, nor no diſſayteful wordes be pronounced with the tonge, nor that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyinge in wayt be not hyd in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynd, but that, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the will poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth: yea &amp; let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpeche declare the
<pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:8976:24"/> ſame. For now is Chriſt hym ſelf redy, which adornyd that table, and he dothe alſo conſecrate this, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we now haue. For it is not man which (conſecracion of the table be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet forthe) doth make the body and bloud of Chriſt: but it is Chriſt whiche is crucifyed for vs. The wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des be ſpoken by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſtes mouth, but they be conſecrated by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>De ſacrorum perttcipacione miſterioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>municare nole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, nec oracione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dignus eſt intereſſe, to, iiii. fo, ccxi, Hom. lx, Ioh. Euang.</head>
                  <p>Parentes do often put their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern to other to be norſyd, but I ſaye ſaithe chriſt do not ſo. But w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my fleſhe I do noriſhe, I put my ſelf vnto you, willyng you al to be gentelmen, &amp; pretending good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8976:25"/> of you of thinges to come. Which do here geue my ſelf to you, moch more in the world to come. I haue willed to be your brother. I haue taken fleſhe &amp; bloud for you: vnto you agayn I geue that ſame fleſh &amp; bloud, by which I am made your coſyn. This bloud maketh to vs a floryſhing ymage of a kinge. This bloud is an honor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> can not be done awaye. This bloude doth not ſuffer the gentelnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule to conſume, euer freſhinge it &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing it. For of meats blod ſprin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginge in vs, is not ſtrayghtwaye made that, but ſome other thinge. But this is not ſo: but by and by it wateryth the mynde, and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in a certayn grace, vertue, or ſtrengthe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Aa"/> This miſtical bloud put<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth away deuelles, and cauſeth them to be farre away, and calleth Angelles to vs, And the Lorde of
<pb n="xix" facs="tcp:8976:25"/> Angels, for where they ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes bloud, deuils fly away, and angel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les come, to this bloudeſhed waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth all the worlde.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>More ſaynges of Chriſoſtom in his Homily .xxiiii. 1. Cor. x.</head>
               <p>The thinge that is in the chalice is that which ranne oute of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſyde, &amp; we are partakers of it.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Liber. iiii. cap. iii. de dignitate ſacerdotali.</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="G"/> 
                     <hi>O</hi> Greate good will of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs, O myracle, he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſyttethe vpon the right hande of his father in heauen aboue, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in mennes handes, in the tyme of ſacrifice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Homili. <hi>XVii.</hi> Epiſcopi. ad heb. ix. ca.</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="P"/> There is one bodye of Chriſt day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly offered in ſacrifice, and one Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:8976:26"/> in euerye place where the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, which is here in this place full, and there in that place alſo full or hole.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Homil. ad Antiochenum populum</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="H"/> Helias the Prophete aſcending vp, left his mantell vnto his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, but the ſonne of God aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge vp into heauen, lefte vnto vs his owne fleſhe. As for Helyas leauinge his mantell vnto his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, left it from him ſelfe: but our ſauioure Chriſt hath both left his fleſhe with vs, and alſo taken it with hym ſelfe in his Aſcencion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Homil, xlv, ſuper Iohannem,</head>
                  <p>It is not man that maketh our Lordes bodye and bloude, of thoſe thinges ſet forth vpon the table to be conſecrated, but it is Chriſte that was crucified for vs: The wordes are pronounced of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preiſt,
<pb n="xx" facs="tcp:8976:26"/> and theſe thynges, (breade and wyne) are conſecrated by Goddes power and grace, for he ſayde: <hi>This is my body.</hi> By theſe wordes the breade and wyne are conſecrated.</p>
                  <p>If a man loke in howe muche he is bounde to fleſh and bloud,<note place="margin">To. li, 6, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> alogoru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Cap. 5.</note> &amp; to be able to be made nigh to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed &amp; ſimple nature, then diligentlye ſhould he vnderſtand that it were mete to honor preiſts by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of the holy goſt,<note place="margin">Sacerdotes honorandi</note> for by them theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries be fulfilled, &amp; other no leſſe then theſe, beinge ſo greate, either becauſe of our helth, or els becauſe of dignitie. For they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inhabit erth and be conuerſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in it, hath deſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued to diſpence heuenly thinges.<note place="margin">Poteſtatem ligandi et ſoluendi dedit h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nibus non Angelis nec arch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> angelis.</note> &amp; they haue receaued power, whiche god nether gaue to Aungels, nor Archaungels: nor it was not ſayde to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what things ſoeuer ye bind on earth, they ſhalbe hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de alſo in
<pb facs="tcp:8976:27"/> heuen, and what thinges ſo euer ye looſe, they ſhalbe looſed.</p>
                  <p>The prynces of the world hath alſo a certayn power of byndinge, but which is only laufull in body<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,<note place="margin">Que ſacer dotes agu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in terris, Chriſtus confirmat in celis.</note> but this bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de which is commyt to preiſtes, it goyth to the ſoule &amp; paſſeth to heuen. That thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that preiſtes do beneth, God dothe alſo confirme in heauen, and corroborateth the ſentence, for it is no other thinge to be called, but woodnes to contempne that miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye,<note place="margin">Sine ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mento Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtie nulla ſalus nec pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſa red. duntur.</note> with oute which neither is hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, nor thoſe good things that be promyſed ſhoulde be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, for none ſhalbe able to go into the kingdome of heauen, but thoſe that be borne agayne of water and of the ſpirite. And he that eateth not the fleſhe of oure LORDE and drynketh not his bloude, ſhall not haue lyfe euerlaſtynge,
<pb n="xxi" facs="tcp:8976:27"/> which be made with no other han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des then with the holy handes of the preſt,<note place="margin">Solue ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdos co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrat.</note> nor can haue the rewarde of promyſes, nor eſcape the fyer of hell, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office of theſe things. Theſe be they that bring vs forth in a ſpirituall generation, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute them by the generation of baptim, by them we be clothed with Chriſt, and by them we be ioyned to the ſonne of God, by them we be alſo made members of that bleſſed head.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Saynt Ambroſe was within .cclxxx. after Chriſt in his .iiii. boke of ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. the .xiiii. cap.</head>
            <p>WHo is the author of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, but our Lorde Ieſus? theſe ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen, for all counſell is frome
<pb facs="tcp:8976:28"/> heauen, but verely greate &amp; God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is the myracle, that God ray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned from heauen to the people An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles foode.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.</note> And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people labored not, and yet did eate, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> Thou pera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture ſayeſt: my bread is had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly in vſe, but this bread, is bread before the ſacramentall wordes, but after conſecration hathe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proched, of bread is made the fleſh of Chriſt. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Let vs therfore fortefye and approue this: how it which is breade can be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Chriſt by conſecration? Of what wordes than and of whoſe ſayinges conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth the conſecration? euen of our Lord Ieſu, for by al other thinges which are ſpoken, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> prayſe is offered to God, and prayer &amp; ſupplication is made for the people, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge &amp; for other thinges. But wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is come to paſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (worthy to be honoured) muſt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated
<pb n="xxii" facs="tcp:8976:28"/> now the preiſt vſeth not his owne worde, but the wordes of Chriſte. Therfore the worde of Chriſt doth make or conſecrate this ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Whiche word of Chriſt? it truly, by the whiche al thinges are made. The Lorde commaunded, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen was made. The Lord commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, and the earth was made. The lord commaunded &amp; the ſeas was made. The Lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded &amp; eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry creature was begotten &amp; borne. Seeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> than how mighty in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the word of God is? therfore, if ſo great power, ſtrength: &amp; vertu be in the word of our lorde Ieſu, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinges whiche were not, began to be: howe muche more is it able to worke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the things were, might be chaunged into another thing? hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was not, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea was not,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earthe was not. But here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid ſpeaking of god, he ſpake the word, &amp; the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:8976:29"/> were made, he commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and the thinges was created. Than let me anſwer, it was not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of chriſt before the conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but after the conſecration I ſay vnto the, that now it is the body of Chriſte. He ſpake the word and it was done, he commaunded and it was created. Thou thy ſelfe was: but thou was an olde creature. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou was dedicated to God &amp; baptiſyd, thou began to be a new creature. Wylt thou knowe how new a creature thou arte? Euery man (ſaith Saynt Paule) is by Chriſt anew creature, here therfore,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> lo, the worde of Chriſte hathe bene wonte to chaunge euery creature: and chaungeth whan it will the cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtomes and ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of nature. Thou requireſt how? Harken. And fyrſt of all let vs take example of Chriſtes generation. The cuſtome
<pb n="xxiii" facs="tcp:8976:29"/> is, that man can not be generate but of man and woman, and wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke company: but bycauſe it was our Lordes pleaſure who chooſe this Sacrament, Chriſt was borne of the holy ghoſt, and of a vyrgyn, that is to ſaye: the mediatoure of God and men, Chriſte Ieſus verye man. Than thou ſeeſt, that againſt the cuſtome and order of nature, a man was borne of a vyrgin. Take an other example.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14</note> The children of Iſraell was oppreſſed of the Egi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptians, cloſed in with the ſea on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſyde, by the commaundement of God Moyſes touched the water with his rodde, and the water deui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded her ſelfe a ſonder: which vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was not after the cuſtome of her nature, but according to the grace of the heauenly commaundement. Take an other example.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod,</hi> 15.</note> The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell was thurſtye, and
<pb facs="tcp:8976:30"/> came to a fountayne of water, the whiche was bytter, not able to be dronke: Holy Moyſes dyd caſt a tre into the water, and it was made ſwete which before was bitter, that is to ſaye: it chaunged the cuſtome of nature, and toke the ſwetnes of grace. Take alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth example It fortuned as a man was felling doune a tre beſides the floude Ior<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dayne,<note place="margin">4, <hi>Reg.</hi> 6.</note> the axe hed full into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſonke to the botome (as the cuſtome of Iron is to do) the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Heleſeus dyd caſt a ſticke of woode into the water, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately the Iron came vp &amp; ſwym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med aboue the water, the whiche verely is againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of yron. For the ſtuffe &amp; ſubſtaunce of Iron is moch heuyer than is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> element of water. Doſt thou the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amples vnderſtande how mightily the heauenly worde worketh? yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb n="xxiiii" facs="tcp:8976:30"/> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly worde hath wrought in an earthy fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayne, yf it hath wrought in other thinges, doth not it alſo worke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauenly ſacramentes?<note place="margin">Pauis f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eory 9 chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſti.</note> than y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt learned y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of bread may be made the body of Chriſt. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wine and water is put into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> but it is made bloude by the conſecration of the heauenly word But perauenture thou wilt ſaye, I ſe not the forme of bloude. Euen as thou haſt taken the ſimilitude of death in baptyme,<note place="margin">Reſpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſo doſt thou drinke the ſimilitude of the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe bloude, that there be no feare of bloude, and yet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it maye worke the price of redemption. Thou haſt therfore learned, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing which thou takeſt is the bodye of Chriſt, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloude of our Lorde.</p>
            <p>Wilt thou know that it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate with heauenly wordes. Here what the words be. The preſt
<pb facs="tcp:8976:31"/> ſayth: Make (ſayth he) this oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on enrolled, reaſonable whiche is a fygure of the bodye and bloude of our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt:<note place="margin">Qui pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</note> whiche the daye afore that he ſuffered, he toke breade in his holy handes, loked to heauen, to his holy father almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, geuynge thankes, bleſſed, brake, and beinge broken, gaue it to his Apoſtels and Diſciples, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge: <hi>Take and eate of this all, for this is my body that ſhall be broken for many.</hi> And in lyke maner, he toke the cuppe after he had ſupped (the daye before that he ſhoulde ſuffer) and loked to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, to the holy father almyghtye, euerlaſtynge God, geuynge than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, bleſſed, gaue it to his Apoſtels and Diſciples, ſayinge: <hi>Take and drynke of this all, for this is my bloude.</hi> Se al theſe be the wordes of the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelyſt vnto, <hi>Take ye,</hi> whether it be the body or bloude, then be the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des
<pb n="xxv" facs="tcp:8976:31"/> of Chriſte: <hi>Take and drynke of it all,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> Afore it is conſecrate it is breade:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Corpus chriſti eſt.</note> but when the wordes of Chriſte come, it is the bodye of Chriſt. Fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thermore heare hym ſayinge: <hi>Take and eate of it all: this is my body,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> And afore the wordes of Chriſte, the cuppe is full of wyne and water: When the wordes of Chriſte haue wroughte, there is the bloude made, whiche hath redemed the people. Then ſe in howe greate kyndes is the word of Chriſt myghty and able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert all maner of thinges. Further more, the Lorde Ieſus hym ſelfe doth teſtifie vnto vs, that we may take his bodye and bloude, ſhould we then doubte of his fayth and wytneſſynge.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> de Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis</note> Nowe come with me to my propoſition. It is ſurelye a greate and worſhypfull thynge, that he dyd raygne Manna from heauen to the Iewes. But vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,
<pb facs="tcp:8976:32"/> what is more, the Manna from heauen, or the body of Chriſt? Surelye the bodye of Chriſte, whiche is maker of heauen. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="O"/> Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore he that did eate Manna is deade. But he that hath eaten this bodye, it ſhalbe to hym for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuenes of ſynnes, and he ſhall neuer dye. Therfore thou ſayſt not in vayne Amen, So be it. Now thou confeſſinge in ſprite that thou takeſt the bodye of Chriſte, the preiſt ſaith to the, The body of Chriſt. And thou faiſte Amen. That is true that which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth hath the deſyre. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> It is to be knowen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in pronounſing of theſe wordes.<note place="margin">Bread is turned into the body of Chriſte.</note> 
               <hi>This is my bodye,</hi> a miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye is done. And breade is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into Chriſtes bodye. If thou aſke how? we leauinge theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges not certayne, do affirme that which is of auctorities, that is
<pb n="xxvi" facs="tcp:8976:32"/> to ſay, that the ſubſtaunce of bread and wine, is conuerted into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtaunce of the bodye and bloude of our lorde. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/>
            </p>
            <p>And we be not aſhamed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that we knowe not the maner of turnynge. For the thynges that remayne of the former ſubſtaunce,<note place="margin">accidentia manent</note> be accidentes, that is: the coloure, ſauour, fourme, and weyghte. Nor yet they do make the bodye of Chriſt, nor can be grounded therin. But if it be aſked where they be founded, we ſaye,<note place="margin">Hic deo ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s manet ſine ſubiectodo uirtute di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uina,</note> that by diuyne miracle, they be ſuſtayned without ſubſtaunce.</p>
            <p>This is truely a greate miſterye, and vnſearcheable. We be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to beleue: we be not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to diſcuſſe,<note place="margin">We be commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded to be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue, but not to diſcuſſe.</note> all thinges that the Lorde wolde he dyd in hea-and in earth. And becauſe ſo he wolde, ſo it was. So thoughe
<pb facs="tcp:8976:33"/> the figure of breade and wyne be ſeene: yet after the conſecration, we muſte beleue nothinge els, but the fleſhe and bloude of Chriſte. Wherefore the truth doth ſaye to his Diſciples: This is my fleſhe for the lyfe of the worlde, and that I might ſpeake more maruelouſly it is playnely none other but that which was borne of the virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye, and ſuffered on the croſſe, and roſe out of the graue. This I ſaye is it. And therfore is it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe of Chriſt, which for the lyfe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde yet to daye is offered, the breade of angelles is made the meate of men: wherfore he ſayth: I am the lyuely bread which cam doune from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Alſo, the breade which I will gyue is my fleſhe for the lyfe of the world. By theſe two ſentences it is geuen openly to be vnderſtanded, that this breade and that, be not
<pb n="xxvii" facs="tcp:8976:33"/> two, but one breade and one fleſhe, and withoute doute is made one bodye. That verely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſurely, which was taken of the virgyn, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that was buryed, that aroſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne and aſcended into heauen, &amp; ſitteth on the right hande of God the father, and which is to come, to Iudge the quicke &amp; the dead. And that thou mayſte knowe this to be a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the figure of this went before, afterwarde, know how gret a Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it is,<note place="margin">Of the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie &amp; gret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament.</note> ſe what he ſaith. As ofte as ye ſhall do this, ſo ofte ſhal ye make a remembrance of me vntil I come. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Ee"/> Therfore we hauing in mind his moſt glorious paſſion, &amp; reſurrection from hel, &amp; his aſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we do offer vnto this ſpotles ſacrifice, reaſonable hoſt, bloudleſſe offering, this holy bread and Cuppe of lyfe euerlaſtyng. We bothe aſke and pray the that thou
<pb facs="tcp:8976:34"/> woldeſt take this oblation into thy high alter, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> handes of thy holy Angelles, as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte voucheſafe to receaue the rewardes of thy Iuſt ſeruante Abell, and the ſacrifice of our patriarke Abraham, and that which the high preiſt Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech hathe offered vnto the. Therfore how oft ſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue? what ſaith the Apoſtel to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. Howe ofte ſo euer we do take, we do ſhow the Lordes death. If we ſhowe deathe, we ſhowe remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſynnes:<note place="margin">Remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of ſynnes.</note> howe ofter ſo euer bloude is ſhed, it is ſhed in remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſynnes. I muſte alwaye take it that my ſynnes maye be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted. I that alwaye do ſynne muſte alwaye haue a mediſon.<note place="margin">De Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis. li. <hi>6.</hi> Cap. <hi>1</hi>
               </note> For as our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt is the true ſonne of God, not as men by grace, but as a ſonne of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of his father: So is it the
<pb n="xxviii" facs="tcp:8976:34"/> veray fleſhe (as he ſayde) and the veray bloude whiche we drinke. But perauenture ye may ſaye, how veray fleſhe? I that ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimilitude ſe not the truthe of the bloude. Fyrſt I tolde you of the worde of Chriſt, which worketh that it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to chaunge and conuert kyndes of nature inſtitute. Farthermore whan his diſciples dyd not take the worde of Chriſt, but hearinge that he wolde gyue them his fleſhe to eate, and his bloude to drynke, they went backe, yet Peter onely ſayde, thou haſt the wordes of lyfe, and ſhal I go from the? Therfore leaſt that mo ſhoulde ſaye ſo, as ther were a certayne fear of bloud, but that the grace of the redemer might abyde ſtyll, therfore in a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude thou takeſt the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: but yet thou getteſt the grace and vertue of the true nature.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:8976:35"/>
               <head>In his firſte prayer at maſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> O Lorde reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bringe thy paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, do come vnto thyne alter, all though I be a ſynner, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may offer to the that ſacrifice, which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> dydeſt ordayne and commaunde to be offered, for our ſaluation in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of the.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Aduerſus uigilantium.</head>
                  <p>I reproue all opinions agaynſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche &amp; openly condempne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Amb. de fide ab Garcianum.</head>
                  <p>Away with Argumentes where fayth is ſought</p>
                  <p>Thomas had a greate cauſe to maruel when he ſaw Chriſtes body brought into the houſe with oute hurte through, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gates cloſed, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che coulde not be paſſed through with mennes bodyes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <pb n="xxix" facs="tcp:8976:35"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Saynt Ambroſe in his boke</hi> De ſpiritu ſancto, lib, iii. Cap. xii.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> It is therfore no meane queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therfore we ſhould the more diligently conſyder, what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fote<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtole. For we reade in a nother place, heauen is my throne, and the earthe the foteſtole of my fete. But yet the earth is not to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of vs, becauſe it is a creatur of God. And yet let vs ſe though, leſt the Prophete name the earth to be worſhypped, which our Lord Ieſus toke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> takinge of fleſhe. So the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the foteſtole let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth be vnderſtand, &amp; then by the earth the fleſh of Chriſt which we do now worſhip (alſo in the miſteries) and which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtelles (as we haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayd) worſhiped in our lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu, for chriſt is not deuided but one.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:36"/>
            <head>S. Auguſtyne. Fo. xxxviii Here begynneth the ſayinge of Saynt Auguſtyne, <hi>priore contione. Pſal.</hi> 33. <hi>Cum fugerit Dauid Saul perſecutorem iniquiens ait.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Q"/> 
               <note place="margin">Chriſt was bor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne in his own ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note>CHriſt was borne in his owne handes. Howe can that be in man? Who can vnderſtand, for who is borne in his owne handes? A man may be borne in other mens handes, no manne is borne in his owne handes. Howe it may be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande in Dauid (after the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) I fynde not, in Chryſte we fynde. Chriſt truely was borne in his owne handes, when he (geuing his bodye) ſayth: <hi>This is my body,</hi> That body verely was borne in his owne handes.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Contra literas Petiliani. Lib. ii.</head>
               <pb n="xxx" facs="tcp:8976:36"/>
               <p>It is another paſſeouer that the Iewes do celebrate with a ſhepe, &amp; an other that we celebrate in the bodye and bloude of our Lorde. Chriſte in Sacramentes, fewe in nombre, mooſt excellent in ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, hath bounde together a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhyppe of newe people. As bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſme is conſecrate in the name of the Trinitie,<note place="margin">Ad Ianua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rium. Epi. <hi>118.</hi>
                  </note> and the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge of the bodye and bloude of hym. And if anye other thynge be commended therin Scriptures ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall, it doth playnely appeare, what tyme the Apoſtels toke fyrſt the bodye and bloude of oure lorde, that they dyd not take it faſtynge, is it therfore to accuſe maliciouſly the vniuerſall churche, that it is alway receaued of the faſtynge? For that cauſe it pleaſed the holye goſt, that in the honour of ſo great a ſacrament, that the bodye of our
<pb facs="tcp:8976:37"/> Lorde ſhoulde firſte enter into the Chriſtian mouth before other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Therfore thoroughout all the worlde this maner is obſerued. Let vs heare oure Lorde, not ſpeaking of the ſacrament of baptyſme,<note place="margin">De pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites et re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſionem.</note> but of the ſacrament of his holy table. Except ye eate my fleſhe, &amp; drynke my bloude, ye ſhall not haue lyfe in you. What do we ſeke more? What can they aunſwer to this? excepte with ſtubbornes they do bend their brawling ſynowes, contrary to the cleare trueth. Was not the Lorde ones offered in hym ſelfe? and yet in the Sacrament, not onely by al the ſolempnities of Eaſter, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery daye to the people is offered. Nor he doth not lye,<note place="margin">Omni die populus immolatur</note> which beynge demaunded, dyd aunſwer him to be offered. For if the Sacrament had not a certaine ſimilitude of thoſe thynges whereof they be Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,
<pb n="xxxi" facs="tcp:8976:37"/> they ſhulde not be Sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes at all. Therfore they be cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led ſacramentes, becauſe one thing is ſeene in them, &amp; another thinge vnderſtanded. That which is ſene hath a bodelye forme:<note place="margin">Epiſtola ad bonifa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium,</note> that whiche is vnderſtande, hath a ſpirituall frute. He that taketh the myſterye of an vnitie, and kepeth not the bonde of peace, he taketh not the bonde of miſtery for hym ſelfe, but a wytneſſe agaynſt hym ſelf. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member my ſayinge when I dydde treat of Sacramentes, I told you that after the words of Chriſt, that whiche is offered is called breade, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> but when the wordes of Chriſte is ſpoken, then it is not called bread,<note place="margin">Ante con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pa. dr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. poſt conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>onem cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pus appel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latur.</note> but it is called the bodye. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Lordes prayer we pray, Oure breade, but as it is ſayde in greke, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſuperſubſtancial, not that whiche goeth into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye
<pb facs="tcp:8976:38"/> but that of eternall lyfe, which vpholdeth the ſubſtaunce of our ſoule.<note place="margin">Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tidie.</note> Take dailye, that maye dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye profite the. So lyue that thou maiſte dailye deſerue to take it. Dailye holy Iob dyd offer for his children ſacrifice, leſt any thinge either in heart, or worde they ſhold offend. Therfore thou heareſt that as often ſoeuer the ſacrifyce is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, the death of the lorde, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rection of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, the aſcention of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord is ſignified, &amp; remiſſion of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daily bread of euerlaſting lyfe thou doeſt not take? He that hathe a wounde, deſireth a medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, it is a wounde that we be vnder ſynne. The heauenly &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable ſacrament is a mediſon. The fyrſt ſacramentes which were obſerued by the law,<note place="margin">Contra Fauſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. lib <hi>19.</hi> ca, <hi>13,</hi>
                  </note> were for meſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyngers of Chriſte to come, whiche when Chriſte dyd fullfill with his
<pb n="xxxii" facs="tcp:8976:38"/> commynge were taken awaye. And therefore were they taken awaye, becauſe they were fulfilled. For Chriſt came not to breake the law but to fulfill it. And there be other inſtitucions greater in vertu, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in profyte, eaſyar to be done, fewer in nombre, as by the Iuſtice of God ſhewed into the libertie, to them that be called the childern of God. If in the olde tyme righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe men, for this foreſhowinge ſacramentes &amp; figures of thinges not yet fulfilled,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dani,</hi> 13, 2, <hi>Mac,</hi> 7,</note> were redy to ſuffer harde &amp; horrible thinges: as of the thre children whiche in Danyell is manifeſt, and of the Machabes, how moche the more now, for the baptyſme of Chriſt, for the bodye or Euchariſt of Chriſt, euery Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ought to be more redy to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer all maner of thinges. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/>
               </p>
               <p>We worſhyppe the fote ſtole of
<pb facs="tcp:8976:39"/> his fete, for it is holy. What is the foteſtole of his fete? The earth is the foteſtole of his fete. Here I am in a doubte: I am afrayde to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe the earth, leſt he ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempne me, that made heauen and earth.</p>
               <p>Agayne, I am afrayde not to worſhippe the ſtoole of my LOR<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>DES feete, becauſe the Pſalme nynetye and eyghte ſayinge vnto me: Thou ſhalte worſhippe the ſtole of his fete. I aſke, what is the ſtole of his fete? Beynge thus toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to and fro, I turne me to Chriſt for hym I ſeke here and fynde, how that without violence of Goddes honor, the earth maye be worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and ſo withoute violation of GODDES honoure, the ſtole of his fete may be worſhypped.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> For chriſt toke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earthe, earthe, for the fleſhe is of the earthe, and
<pb n="xxxiii" facs="tcp:8976:39"/> he toke fleſh of the fleſh of Mary, and becauſe in that fleſhe he wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked here,<note place="margin">We eate the ſame fleſh that was bor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of the vyrgin Mary.</note> and gaue the ſame fleſhe to be eaten of vs for our ſaluation no man eateth that fleſhe, except he fyrſt haue worſhipped it. It is ſo founde oute how ſouche a fote<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtole of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde maye be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> And not onely that we ſynne not in worſhippinge of it, but that we ſynne in not worſhippynge of it. And though it be neceſſary that it be viſible celebrate, I wolde not that ye toke my wordes ſo groſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as they which beleuinge me to cutte forth certayne peces of my body and to geue them in meate: But I haue commended vnto you a certayne ſacrament vnder theſe wordes, my fleſhe ſhalbe geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you vnder ſacramentes that it may be eaten, not accordinge to this groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſe: but ſpiritually it muſt
<pb facs="tcp:8976:40"/> be vnderſtande: and ſpiritually vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtanded, it wyll geue life vnto you, for viſibly muſt this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be celebrate, but my fleſhe ſhalbe vnder the ſame inuiſible, and inuiſible there beynge preſent it muſt be vnderſtand.<note place="margin">Viſibiliter celebretur ſed inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligitur.</note> And though it be neceſſary, it to be celebrate vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible it muſt nedes be vnderſtande inuiſible.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e .ii. Pſal. <hi>33</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DAuid fled to Achimalech, and before him he chaunged his countenaunce,<note place="margin">Fugit Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid ad A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimelech, &amp; eoram to mutauit multu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>1,</hi> reg, <hi>21,</hi>
                  </note> and lefte hym, and went his wayes, for there was a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice after the order of Aaron, &amp; afterwarde he of his body &amp; bloud inſtitute a Sacrifice after the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Melchiſedech. He chaunged his countenaunce in the preiſthod, he lefte the people of the Iewes, and came to the Gentyles. He was borne in his owne handes, when
<pb n="xxxiiii" facs="tcp:8976:40"/> he gaue his bodye and his bloude. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Q"/> He toke into his own handes, that the faithfull knoweth, and he dyd beare hym ſelfe after a manner, when he ſayde: <hi>This is my body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pſal contione primo,</note> The Sacrifice of Aaron is take away, and the Sacrifice is begonne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the order of Melchiſedech. Therfore hathe he chaunged his countenaunce. I can not tell how<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who is this? I can not tell who. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="R"/> I knowe who, for our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte is knowen in bodye and bloude. He woulde be oure health, wherfore he hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs his body &amp; bloude of his owne humilite, for except he had ben meke, he wolde neither haue ben eaten nor dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ken.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sermo,</hi> 4.</note> Our daily bread whether we aſke exhibition neceſſarye to the bodye of the father, ſignifienge in bread, what ſoeuer is neceſſarye to vs, or we do vnderſtande that daiely
<pb facs="tcp:8976:41"/> bread which we are wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to receaue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alter. We aſke wel, that he may geue it vs. For what is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we aſke or praye for, but that we commyt none euell, wherby we be ſeperate from ſouche breade, and the worde of God that is daiely preached is breade, for becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is breade of the ſoule. For when this lyfe ſhall paſſe away,<note place="margin">Sacramen. altaris.</note> we do not ſeke for that breade whiche honger ſeketh for, nor we ought not to take the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the alter, that we ſhalbe ther with Chriſte, whoſe bodye we take, nor the wordes ought not to be ſayde to vs, whiche we ſay vnto you, nor the boke is not to be redde that we ſhal ſe hym which is Gods worde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm.</hi> 46</note> by whiche all thinges be made. The Lorde Ieſus hathe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted by promyſe of eternal lyfe, to eate his fleſhe and drinke his bloude, as it is manifeſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
<pb n="xxxv" facs="tcp:8976:41"/> in theſe wordes. He that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth my fleſh &amp; drinketh my bloud. Therfore they that now do eat and drink, let them think what they eat &amp; what they drinke, leaſt (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith) they eate and drinke their owne iudgemente, not iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge the Lordes body. They that eat not and drinke not, let them make haſte to ſuche dayntyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge hidden, Chriſt doth daiely feed his table is that whiche is ſet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myddes. What cauſe is it,<note place="margin">Chriſtus quotidis paſcit.</note> Oh he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears, that ye ſee the table, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not to the daynties? perauen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture ye thinke,<note place="margin">Fideles no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt quo modo caro manduca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur. Infideles neſciunt.</note> how is the Lordes fleſhe eaten, and his bloude dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> infideles it is not knowen, but the faithful know. Come to the profeſſion, and thou haſt aſſoyled the queſtion. Let the faithefull lyue well that they eate not into
<pb facs="tcp:8976:42"/> iudgement and drinke. Thinkinge vpon your degrees, and kepinge your profeſſion, come to the fleſhe of our Lorde, vntill the worlde be ended. Oure Lorde is aboue, but yet for all that, the truthe of the Lorde is here with vs: The bodye wherin he aroſe in that kind, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth to be in one place, but the very body in forme of breade, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where,<note place="margin">Corpus Chriſti in omni alta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,</note> that is to ſay: in euery aulter where it is conſecrate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sermo. ii. de uerbis Apoſtoli.</head>
               <p>We haue hard the true maſter, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> godly redemer mans ſauiour, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to vs our praiſe, his blud. For he hath ſpoken to vs of his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy &amp; bloud, that he called his body meat, &amp; his bloud drink. A ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the faithfull, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfull knowe, for hearyng, what other thinge do they heare but lyfe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mending ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che meate &amp; ſouche drinke, ye ſhall
<pb n="xxxvi" facs="tcp:8976:42"/> haue (ſaithe he) lyfe in you,<note place="margin">Qui inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger aſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dere potu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>it, conſumi no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> potuit.</note> if you eate when ſome wer offended, that this ſaying was herd. He aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: dothe this offende you? ye wene that of this bodye that ye ſe I am about to make partes, &amp; to cut a ſonder my me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, &amp; to geue to you: what and yf ye ſe the ſonne of man aſcendynge where he was before? Surelye he that coulde go vp hole, coulde not be conſumed. Therfore of his body &amp; his bloude hathe he geuen to vs a holſome refection, and ſo greate a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his holenes doth he aſſoyle. For ſo arte thou refreſhed, that it can not fayle, wherevpon thou ſhalte be refreſhed. Eate lyfe, drinke lyfe, thou ſhalte haue lyfe, and the lyfe is hole, and that ſhall be, that is to ſay: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodye &amp; bloude of Chriſte ſhalbe lyfe to euery one, yf that whiche in the ſacrament
<pb facs="tcp:8976:43"/> is taken viſiblye, be eaten ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, in very truth be dronken ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually.<note place="margin">Caro nihil prodeſt. Spiritus eſt qui uiui ficat. Super Ioh Cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> We haue harde him ſelfe ſaying: It is the ſpirite that quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth, fleſhe profiteth not at all, your fathers haue eaten Manna and be deade. Whye be they deade? For that they dyd ſe they beleued. That, that they dydde not ſe, they vnderſtode not. Moyſes dyd eate, Aaron did eate, Phinees dyd eate, and manye other dyd eate, whiche pleaſed the Lorde, and were not deade, for they vnderſtode a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meate ſpiritually: ſpirituallye they dyd hunger, and ſpirituallye they taſted, that ſpirituallye they myghte be fylled. For to daye we take a viſible meate: but the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment is one thynge, and the vertu of the ſacrament is another. Verye manye do take of the aulter and dye,<note place="margin">Altare</note> and in takynge they dye.
<pb n="xxxvii" facs="tcp:8976:43"/> Wherfore the Apoſtle ſayth: he ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and drinketh his iudgement. Was not the Lordes morſell poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to Iudas? and yet he receiued:<note place="margin">De Iuda.</note> and when he receiued, the enemye entred into hym. Not that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued an euell thynge: but that he beyng euyl, receaued that which was good. Se therfore brethern, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaue the heauenly breade ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, bringe innocency vnto the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Synnes though they be daye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet they be not deadly. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="N"/> Afore ye come to the aulter, take hede what ye ſaye: forgeue vs our treſpaces. He that eateth my fleſhe and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth my bloude,<note place="margin">Ioh, ca. <hi>6,</hi>
                  </note> hath lyfe euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge. That is not geuen in the meate whiche we take to ſuſtayne the fleſhe, but it is in this meate and drynke that is in the body and bloude of our lorde. For he that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not it, hath not lyfe, and he
<pb facs="tcp:8976:44"/> that taketh it, hath lyfe, and that euerlaſtinge. The ſacrament of this thynge, that is of the vnite of the bodye and bloude of Chriſt, In ſome place it is done daily. In ſome by certayne ſpace of dayes betwene. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes table let it be prepared, and of the Lordes table it is taken, of ſome to lyfe, of ſome to deathe, of this matter ſe more in the ſixte of Iohn. Here is the ſayinge of the Lordes body, whiche he ſayde he woulde geue to be eaten for eternall lyfe. He dyd expounde the maner of thattribution, and of his gyfte. He that abydeth in me and I in hym,<note place="margin">Tractus ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per Iohan nom. <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note> &amp; hath eaten a token &amp; hath dronken, that we might be in his bodye, vnder that heade in his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers, eatinge his fleſh, not leuinge his vnitie: many hearinge theſe thinges (not vnderſtanding) were
<pb n="xxxviii" facs="tcp:8976:44"/> offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded for they thought not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge theſe thinges, but fleſh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were to ꝑceiue after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh is deth. And yet ſo it behoueth to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that it ſhoulde not be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande of all the ſecrete thinges of God, it muſt make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> attempt not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, for theſe, dyd ſome ſhrynke from God, ſpeaking ſuche thinges. And in thoſe wordes they dyd not beleue our Lord Ieſu Chriſt, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king a greate thing, couering a cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne grace, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they wolde, ſo they vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, &amp; after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner of men. For Ieſus might that: or Ieſus dyd dyſpoſe that the fleſhe wherewith the worde was clothed (as cut in peces) deſtribute to the beleuers in hym,<note place="margin">Quomodo caro non prodeſt quicquam,</note> the fleſhe auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth no thinge. O Lorde good ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, how doth not the fleſh auayle any thinge? ſeynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſaide: Except one eate my fleſhe and
<pb facs="tcp:8976:45"/> drynke my bloud, he ſhal not haue lyfe in him. Doth not the lyfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit any thinge? And wherefore be we that we be, but that we maye haue euerlaſtynge lyfe, which thou promyſeſte by thy fleſſhe.</p>
               <p>What is it therfore? It profiteth nothinge, the fleſhe profiteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge: But how dydde they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande? truely thus: They vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the fleſhe, as it is rent in the deade bodye, or ſolde in the ſhambles, not as it is quickned with the ſprite.<note place="margin">Let the ſpirite come to the fleſh and it profteth much. <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
                  </note> Let the ſprite come to the fleſhe, and it profiteth moch, or elſe the worde ſhoulde not haue ben made fleſhe, that it might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde in vs. Thou haſt the wordes of lyfe ſayde Peter, one for all, why ſayde he that? but that he beleued. Thou haſt euerlaſtinge lyfe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtracion of thy bodye &amp; bloud: and we beleue and knowe. For yf
<pb n="xxxix" facs="tcp:8976:45"/> we ſhoulde knowe before and then wolde beleue, we ſhoulde neyther be able to knowe nor vnderſtande. What beleue we? and what know we? That thou arte Chriſte the ſonne of the lyuinge God. For y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> arte eternall lyfe, and thou geueſt not in thy fleſh, but that that thou arte. All that the Lorde ſpake of his fleſhe and bloude, and that in the grace of his diſtribution, he promyſed to vs euerlaſtynge lyfe, and therby he woulde to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded the eaters and drinkers of his fleſh &amp; bloud, that they mighte abyde in him, and he in them. And that they vnderſtandinge carnal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, thinges ſpirituall were offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And that they beyng offended periſhinge, comforte of the Lorde might be to the diſciples, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning whom to proue he aſked: And wyll you alſo go away? that
<pb facs="tcp:8976:46"/> the aunſwer of the abyding of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, mighte be knowen to vs: for he knewe who wolde abyde. Therfore all this is auayleable to vs (moſt dearely beloued), that we eate not the fleſhe and bloude of Chriſte in Sacrament (whiche manye euyll doth) but that we eate it vnto the participation of the ſpirite, and drinke it that we abide in the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des bodye as members: that we maye be quickened with his ſprite and be not offended: yea, yf manye eate with vs, and drinke tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallye this Sacramentes whiche ſhall haue in the ende eternall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. For nowe the bodye is mixt, as vpon the flore, but the lorde knoweth who is his. We be ſure brethren that all we that be in the lordes bodye, abyde in hym, that he maye abyde in vs. In this worlde we muſte neades vnto the
<pb n="xl" facs="tcp:8976:46"/> ende lyue amonge the euyll. Not amonge theſe euyll (I ſaye) that blaſpheme Chriſt. For they be ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome founde whiche with tounge do blaſpheme, but many with life: We muſt nedes therfore lyue with them vnto the ende.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>21.</hi> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>25.</hi> De ci. Dei.</note>
               </p>
               <p>He that is in the vnitie of hys bodye, that is in the ioyninge of Chriſtian members: of whoſe body the faythfull communicatinge of the alter, are acuſtomed to take: it is true to be ſayde: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he receaueth Chriſtes body, &amp; drinketh Chriſtes bloude. And by this, heretikes and ſciſmatikes, beyng ſeperated from this vnitie of body, they may ther vpon perceaue a ſacramente: but not to them profitable, yea, rather noyſome, wherby they maye be the more greuouſelye iudged, or more ſlowly deliuered, for that they be not in that bond of peace, which is
<pb facs="tcp:8976:47"/> expreſſed in the ſacrament. Chriſte eaten by partes, and abydeth hole: hole in heauen. He is eaten by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in ſacrament, and abydeth hole in thy harte. He was hole with the father,<note place="margin">Chriſtus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meſtus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigre ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net.</note> when he came into the vyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyn, and fylled her, and he wente not from hym. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> He came in fleſſhe, that men myght eate hym, and he abode hole with the father,<note place="margin">Sermo, Io De uerbis domini</note> that he might fede Aungels. He that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth my fleſhe, and drinketh my bloude, abydeth in me, and I in hym: Howe muſt we vnderſtande? Maye we not here vnderſtande them of whome the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth on, that they eate and drinke theyr iudgement, when they eate that fleſh, and drinke that bloude. Dyd not Iudas (ſeller and betray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er of his maſter)<note place="margin">De Iude</note> touch hym fyrſt in his handes (beinge made a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his fleſhe and bloude) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthely
<pb n="xli" facs="tcp:8976:47"/> with other Diſciples (as more playnely Luke declareth) eate and drinke? dyd he abyde in Chriſt and Chriſt in hym? Many alſo that with fayned harte eate that fleſhe and drink that bloude, or when they haue eaten and dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken be made Apoſtelles: Do they abyde in Chriſt, or Chriſt in them? But ther is a certayn maner of ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinge that fleſhe and drinkynge that bloude, as he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eateth &amp; drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in Chriſt, abydeth in Chriſt, and Chriſt in hym. That is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certayne waye, which waye Chriſt ſawe whan he ſayde theſe wordes my fleſhe is very meate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sermo. xxxii.</head>
               <p>Let vs Ioye moſte derely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louyd, and be glad in the Lorde, whiche in this daye hathe conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to vs miſteryes of holſome comforte. Howe hathe the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:8976:48"/> commended to vs his bodye, and his bloude. How? but of his humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, for yf he were not meke, he wolde nether be eaten nor dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Beholde the highnes of hym. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="R"/> The worde was in the begynninge. Se what meate is euerlaſtinge, Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels eate, highe vertues eate, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ſpirites eate, they eate and be full, and he abideth hole, that he filleth them, and gladdeth them. For who can aſcende to that meat? Becauſe man can not aſcende to that meate,<note place="margin">Quia ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ad hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c nequibat aſcendere, Chriſtus deſcende bat ut pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis fieret.</note> this breade voucheſafe to deſcende to man, and that with vnſpeakable pitie was done: for it was neceſſarye that that table of Aungels ſhould geue mylk, &amp; come to littell ones. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Gg"/> Therfore ye beinge about to come to the aulter of the Lorde, loke out all the priuie pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of your hart, leſt peraduenture there be any ſynnes whiche be not
<pb n="xlii" facs="tcp:8976:48"/> yet healed with almoſe and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge. And feare this: he that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Lordes bodye and bloude vnworthely, he ſhalbe gylty of the bodye and bloude of oure Lorde. Therfore let a man proue him ſelf and ſo let hym eate and drinke of that cuppe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Howe the bodye of Chriſte that honge on the Croſſe is recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and howe not: in his Epiſtle, <hi>ad Hyreneumin expoſiti. Pſal. liiii.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="M"/> NOt this body that ye ſe, ye be about to eate and drink, that bloude whiche they be aboute to ſhed, whiche wyl crucifie me: that, and not that: that inuiſible, and not that viſible. Wherfore it folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth: yf it be neceſſarye that to be celebrate viſible, it is neceſſary, it to be vnderſtande inuiſible.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:8976:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Ad Iulianum comitem,</hi> in the decres .ii. Diſt.</head>
               <p>Frome theſe thinges the pitie of our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt, delyuer vs, and geue vs him ſelfe to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, which ſayde: I am the lyuely breade whiche came downe from heauen: he that eateth my fleſhe, and ſo forthe. But euery one afore he receaue the bodye and bloude of our Lorde Ieſu Chriſte, let hym proue him ſelfe, and (after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente of the Apoſtle) ſo let hym eate of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> breade, and drinke of that cuppe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Hh"/> For whan we muſt receaue hym, we muſte fyrſt go to confeſſion and do penaunce, and diſcuſſe diligently all our actes &amp; noyſome ſynnes, yf we do perceue them. We muſt ſtrayght way make haſte by confeſſion &amp; true penaunce to waſſhe them awaye, leaſte with Iudas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> traytor, hydynge within
<pb n="xliii" facs="tcp:8976:49"/> vs the deuell, we periſhe defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng and concelynge or kepynge our ſynnes frome daye to daye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Auſten in libro Sent. proſperi</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> Therfore we in forme of breade and wyne which we ſe, we do honor thinges inuiſible, that is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe and bloude of Chriſt. Nor in lyke maner we comprehende not thoſe formes, as before conſecration we dyd comprehend them, when we do faithfully confeſſe afore conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to be bread and wyne whiche nature hathe formed: But after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſecration the fleſh and bloude of Chriſt whiche the bleſſinge hath conſecrated, whether vnder a fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure or vnder a trewthe, this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall ſacrament of the cuppe be done the truth ſaythe.</p>
               <p>My fleſhe verely is meate and my bloud verely is drynke: or elſe how ſhal it be great? The bread that I
<pb facs="tcp:8976:50"/> will geue, is my fleſhe for the lyfe of the worlde. Except it be verye fleſhe it cannot geue lyfe:<note place="margin">It is not law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful to tear chr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iſt with teath</note> But by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not leful to deuour chriſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> teath, our Lord wold this bread and wyne, in myſtery truly, his fleſhe and his bloude, by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration of the holy goſte poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to be create, and dayely mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically to be offered. As the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin by the holy goſt, true fleſhe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> oute generation is create, ſo by the ſame, of the ſubſtaunce of breade and wyne, the ſame bodye of Chriſt and his bloude, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="L"/> by vertu of the holy goſt, myſtically is conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.<note place="margin">The bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye of chriſt is both the veritie &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figure</note> The bodye of Chriſt is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and a fygure. It is a veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, when the bodye of Chriſte and bloude, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> throughe vertue of the holy gooſt, is made of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of breade and wyne. And a figure is that, that is oute<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardly
<pb n="xliiii" facs="tcp:8976:50"/> felte. Agayne dayely this oblation (though Chriſt once offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryd) be cauſe we ſynne dayely in ſynnes, withoute whiche mortall infirmitie cannot lyue. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be cauſe we dayely do fall, chriſt dayly, miſticallye for vs is offered within the Catholike chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rch in myſtery of chriſtes body. No<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thinge more is done of a good preſt nothinge leſſe of an euell preiſt,<note place="margin">Nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g more is done of a good Preiſts, then of an euyll</note> for he is not conſecrated in the merite of the conſecratour: But in the worde of the creatour, and in the vertue of the holy ſprite. For if it were in the merite of the preiſt, it ſhould not pertayne to Chriſt. But now as he is which bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> ſo is he whiche by his holy ſprite dothe make this creature of breade his fleſhe, and wyne his bloude.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In Glo. ord. ſuperi, Cor. ca. xi.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:8976:51"/>
               <p>Ther be two maners of eatynge of our Lorde, one is ſacramentall, by whiche,<note place="margin">Ther be two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tings of Chriſte.</note> do eate as well the good as the euell. An other is ſpirituall wherby, the good onely dothe eate. And this is not only to eat Chriſt, and in his ſacrament to take his boodye, but to dwell in Chriſt, and haue Chriſt dwellinge in hym. For they do eate hym ſpiritually whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in the vnitie of the Churche (whiche that ſacrament dothe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifye) doth abide. For he that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordeth frome Chriſt, nor eateth Chriſtes fleſh, though he do dayly to his Iudgement take a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo greate a thinge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Contra. Epiſt. fundament. ca. v.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Ff"/> I wolde not beleue the goſpell except the auctorite of the churche had moued me</p>
               <p>In his .iii. boke .xxii. cha. xxviii. ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon agaynſt Maximinum.</p>
               <pb n="xlv" facs="tcp:8976:51"/>
               <p>The Sacrament of the alter is a figure of Chriſtes death and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of the miſticall body of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> and of his naturall bodye ther in preſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Auguſtin de uerbis diu. Ser. xi.</head>
               <p>That ſame that he alſo ſaithe: Who eateth my fleſhe, and dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth my bloud, dwelleth in me and I in hym, how ſhall we vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de it? Maye we vnderſtande alſo the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of whom the Apoſtle ſpake, that they did eate to them ſelfe, &amp; drinke iudgement, when they did eate the ſame fleſhe and drinke the ſame bloude, the fleſhe it ſelfe? y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloude it ſelfe? Dyd not Iudas the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſellar and betrayer of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, when he dyd eate and drinke (as Luke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Euangeliſt declareth) the Fyrſt Sacrament of the fleſhe &amp; bloude of Chriſt (made his owne handes) dwell in Chriſt or Chriſt in
<pb facs="tcp:8976:52"/> hym? Finally many that with fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned herte eate that fleſhe, &amp; drinke the bloude, or when they haue eaten and dronken, be come apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tataſe, do they dwell in Chriſt, or Chriſtian in them? But withoute doute ther is a certayne maner of eatinge that fleſhe, &amp; drinkinge that bloude, after whiche maner whoſoeuer eateth and drinketh, dwelleth in Chriſt, and Chriſt in hym. Therfore, not in what ſoeuer maner any man eateth the fleſhe of chriſt, and drinketh the bloude of chriſt, he dwelleth in Chriſt, and chriſt in hym: but after a certayne maner, whiche maner he ſaw where he ſayde theſe wordes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ang. de bap. li. v. ca. viii.</head>
               <p>It was neuertheleſſe the bodye of our Lorde alſo vnto them, to whom the Apoſtle ſayde: he that eateth vnworthely, eateth and
<pb n="xlvi" facs="tcp:8976:52"/> drinketh iudgement to hym ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Here foloweth the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of Saynt Ierome vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the .xxi. cha. of Oſe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Haue geuen to the Iewes the eatinge of my bodye. I beinge both the meate &amp; the geſt, ſo dyd he vnderſtande chriſtes wordes.</p>
            <p>Alſo vpon theſe wordes of Mala<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chye the fyrſt chap. ye offered vpon myne alter poluted breade, (ſaithe Ierome) we poluted breade, that is the bodye of Chriſt, when we vnworthelye come to the alter and being foule, do drinke clene bloud: for when ſacramentes be defiled, he whoſe they be is defyled.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ſuper Math. ca. xxvi.</head>
               <p>They ſupping, Ieſus toke bread whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figuratyue paſſeouer was fulfilled, and he had eaten y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe
<pb facs="tcp:8976:53"/> of the lambe with his diſciples, he toke breade, whiche dothe comfort mans harte, and he went ouer to the ſacrament of the trew paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: that as in prefiguringe of hym Melchiſedech y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preiſt of the highe god did, offeringe breade and wyne he dothe alſo repreſent the truthe of his owne bodye. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> God forbyd that I ſpeake any wronge thinge of them whiche ſuccedyd the apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke degre, do with their holy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uthe make the bodye of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ad Litu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Cap, i.</note> by whom eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we be chriſtians. If lay men be commaunded that for pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, they abſtayne frome the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of theyr wyues, what is to be done of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſhope or preiſt, whiche is dailye aboute to offer cleane ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for his owne ſynnes and the peoples. Let vs rede the bokes of the kinges, and we ſhall fynde that the preiſt Abimalech wolde not
<pb n="xlvii" facs="tcp:8976:53"/> fyrſt gyue vnto Dauid and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauntes of the ſhewbreades: But that he dyd aſke hym whether y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſeruantes were clene fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr wyues (not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtraungers, but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their owne wiues) and but that he hard y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they abſtayned yeſterday, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye before frome worke of wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loke, he wolde not haue graunted them the breades whiche he had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore denyed? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> So moche is betwene the ſhewbredes and the body of Chriſt, as is betwene a ſhadowe &amp; a bodye, betwyxte an ymage and the truthe, betwene exemplaries of thinges to come, and thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche were prefigured by the exemplaries.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> Vpon the fyrſt chapter of Tyte Preiſtes do offer dailye for their ſynnes and the peoples alſo, pure ſacrifices, and the preiſt maketh chriſtes bodye at maſſe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8976:54"/>
               <p>Saynt Barnard ſayth: as Chriſt gaue his fleſhe for vs, ſo he gaue his fleſhe to vs, in that miſtery to redeme vs, in this to fede vs.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Petrus Lumbardus, in his .iiii. boke, Chap. xii.</head>
            <p>PEtrus Lumbardus ſayth in his .iiii. boke. and the .xii. chap. After this, it is aſked whether that that the preiſt doth, maye be ſayde properly a ſacrifice or immolation, and whether Chriſt be dayly immo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>late and offered, or onely once?</p>
            <p>Whervnto it may be ſhortly aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: that whiche is offered and conſecrated of the preiſt, is called a ſacrifice and oblation, becauſe it is a memorye and repreſentation of the true ſacrifice, and holy immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation done in the aulter of the croſſe. And Chriſt was once deade
<pb n="xlviii" facs="tcp:8976:54"/> on the croſſe, and ther was offered in hym ſelfe, but he is dayly immo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>late or offered in the Sacrament: becauſe in the ſacrament there is made a memorye of that is once done. Whervpon ſaynt Auguſten in his .xxiii. Epiſtle, written vpon the .vi. chap. vnto the Romaynes, ſayth: We are aſſured that Chriſte ryſing from death, dyeth not now. &amp;c. yet leaſt we ſhoulde forget that is once done, in oure memorye e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery yeare is done, that is to ſaye: as often as the Paſcha is cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate, is Chriſt as often kylled?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="P"/> No: onely a yearely remembraunce repreſenteth that was once done, and cauſeth vs to be moued, as though we ſawe oure LORDE on the croſſe. Alſo Chriſte was once offered in hym ſelfe, and yet is dayly offered in the ſacramente, whiche is thus to be vnderſtande,
<pb facs="tcp:8976:55"/> that in the open ſhewynge of his bodye and diſtinction of his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers he dyd hange onely once vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the croſſe, offerynge hym ſelfe to God the father an hooſt of redemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion effectuall for them whom he hathe predeſtinate. Alſo Saynte Ambroſe. In Chriſt the hoſt was once offered, beinge of power to helth: what do we then? Do we not offer euery daye? and if we offer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery daye, it is done in the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of the death of hym. And the hoſt is one and not many: How one and not manye? becauſe Chriſt is once offered. This is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of that, and the ſame, and alwayes the ſame is offered.</p>
            <p>Therfore this is the ſame ſacrifice, or elſe it maye be ſayde: becauſe it is offered in many places, there be many Chriſtes, whiche is not ſo: But one Chriſt euery where and
<pb n="xlx" facs="tcp:8976:55"/> here full, and there full, ſo as that whiche is offered euery where is one bodye, and ſo alſo one ſacrifice: Chriſt hath offered the hoſt, we do offer the ſame alſo now: but that we do, is a remembraunce of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> Nor ther is no cauſe found of the one inualidite or weaknes be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe it perfiteth the man. Here is gathered, that to be a ſacrifice, and to be ſo called, that is done in the alter, and Chriſt to be onſe offered and daily offered. But other wyſe then, and other wyſe now, and alſo it is ſhewed what is the vertu of this ſacrament, that is to ſaye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of veniall ſynne and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of vertu.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>Hillarye in his boke of the Trinite. lib. viii.</head>
            <p>OVr Lorde leauinge nothinge to the conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the faithful
<pb facs="tcp:8976:56"/> he taughte the effecte of naturall efficacye, ſayinge that they may be one, euen as we be one. I in them, and they in me, that they be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in one. Them I do nowe ſake that do put an vnitie of wyll be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the father &amp; the ſonne: Whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther or no, by the truth of nature, Chriſt be to day in vs, or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde of wyll. For yf we take true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye the worde beinge fleſhe in our Lordes meate: Howe is it not to be eſtemed hym to abyde in vs na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turallye, whiche toke the nature of oure fleſhe, then inſeperable to hym, beinge borne man? And the nature of his fleſhe, to the nature of eternitie, vnder a Sacrament of his fleſhe to vs to be geuen, hathe myngled for ſo we be al one. For euen in Chriſte is the father, and Chriſte in vs. Therefore who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer doth generally deny the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="l" facs="tcp:8976:56"/> in Chriſte, let hym deny fyrſte (not naturally) ether hym in chriſt, or Chriſt to be in hym. For the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Chriſt, and Chriſt in vs, ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth vs to be one in them. If ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore Chriſt haue truely taken fleſh of the bodye of the vyrgyn, and that, that verye man whiche was borne of Marye be Chriſt, and we truely vnder a myſterye, take the fleſhe of his bodye, and ſhalbe one therby becauſe the father is in him and he in vs. Howe is the wyll of vnite affyrmed, whan a propertye naturall by ſacramentes is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyghtlye a Sacrament of vnitie? It is not for the wytte of man, or the wytte of the worlde to ſpeake in Goddes wordes, nor by violent and ſhamefull preachynge of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye wordes, with ſtraunge health, the frowardenes of a wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:8976:57"/> vnderſtandinge to be gotten oute. Let vs reade thoſe thinges that be written, and then we ſhall vſe the offyce of perfight ſaith. For thoſe thinges that we ſpeake of the naturall veritie of Chriſt (except we learne them of Chriſt, whiche we ſpeake of hym) we ſaye and learne folyſhly and wyckedly. For he ſaith: my fleſhe verely is meate, and my bloud verely is drinke. He that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth my fleſhe &amp; drinketh my bloud, he abideth in me, &amp; I in him. There is no place left of doutinge of the verite of fleſhe and bloud. For now by our Lordes profeſſion and our faith, he is verely fleſhe and verely bloude. And theſe taken and dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken do that thinge that bothe we be in Chriſt, and Chriſt in vs, is not this a truthe? let it happen playne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to them not to be trewe, whiche deny y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte is veray trew God.
<pb facs="tcp:8976:57"/> And therfore is he in vs by fleſhe, and we in hym: when he with hym ſelfe, that that we be, he is in God. And for aſmoche as by ſacrament of fleſh &amp; bloud co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate, we be in hym, he beareth witneſſe ſaying, and this worlde doth not nowe ſe me: but you ſhall ſe me. For I am in my father and you in me, and I in you. If he wolde onely the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of will to be vnderſtande, why dyd he expounde a certayne degre and order of vnite to be conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate? but that when he ſhulde be in the father by nature of diuinite, we agayne ſhoulde be in hym, by his corporall natiuite. And he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde in vs myght be beleued to be by a myſtery of ſacramentes. And that this naturall vnite is in vs, he doth thus witnes. He that eateth my fleſhe and drinketh my bloude, dwelleth in me, and I in
<pb facs="tcp:8976:58"/> hym. For none ſhalbe in hym, but in whome he will be. Thou haſt onely his fleſhe taken into hym ſelfe, whiche toke his owne.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Baſell the greate. fo. i. v c.lxi. Anno do.ccc.lxxx.</head>
            <p>BAſill in the rule that he gaue to his brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, taught y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame of the Sacrament, of the whiche by them there is a queſtion put forth after this maner. With what maner of feare,<note place="margin">Timer dei fides.</note> or faith or affect, we owght to take the grace of the bodye and bloude of Chriſt is ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: vnto y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche queſtion thus he an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwereth. The Apſtle teacheth vs feare, ſaying. He that eateth &amp; drin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth vnworthely, he eateth &amp; drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his iudgemente, not iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge the body of our Lorde. The worde of our Lorde teacheth vs
<pb n="lii" facs="tcp:8976:58"/> faith ſayinge: <hi>This is my bodye whiche ſhalbe geuen for you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fides do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cetur de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</note> 
               <hi>this do ye in remembraunce of me.</hi> Agayne the ſayinge of Iohn, that the worde is made fleſſhe, and hath dwelt in vs, and we haue ſene his glory as of the onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſonne of the father, full of grace and truth. Alſo the Apoſtle ſaithe, whiche when he was in the forme of God, thought it no robery to be equall with god. But he dyd make hym ſelfe of no repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion, takynge on hym the ſhape of a ſeruaunte, and became lyke vnto men, and was founde in his apparell as a man, he humbled hym ſelf and becam obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diente vnto the deathe, euen the deathe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe: he therfore that beleuith theſe wordes and conſide<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth the greateneſſe of his glory, and doth meruell at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateneſſe of his humilite, howe ſuche and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:8976:59"/> ſo greate a one was obedient to the father vnto death for our lyfe, I thinke that the ſoule maye be prouoked to affection of God the father, whiche ſpared not his owne ſonne, but gaue hym for vs all, and vnto the loue of his onely begotten ſonne he ſhall the more be prouoked, that he feith hym ſuffer moſt ſhamefull deathe for our redemption.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> Euen as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle dyd ſaye of hym: For the loue of God dothe conſtrayne vs iudgyng that, that if one dyed for all, that they euen whiche lyue, nowe lyue not to them ſelues, but to hym that dyed for them, and roſe agayne. Souche affecte and faith therfore, ſhoulde he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare in his mynde, whiche dothe participate of the breade and cup. If there be greate threatenyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges put for them in the olde lawe,
<pb n="liii" facs="tcp:8976:59"/> that raſhely go to thoſe holy thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche be of men ſanctifyed, What is to be ſayde on hym whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che vnto ſouche &amp; ſo greate a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterye (that is to ſaye of the body &amp; bloude of our Lorde) is folyſhly raſhe? For the greater that any thinge is then they in the temple, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes voyce, ſo moche the more greuouſe and terrible it is to hym that is conſtitute in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clennes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule, raſhely to touch the body of Chriſt, the Apoſtle ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge: he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eateth and drinketh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woorthely, ſhalbe gyltye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body &amp; bloude of our Lorde. yea a more vehement, and more terrible iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement expreſſynge by repeticion: Let man proue hym ſelfe. If a man onely beinge conſtitute in vnclennes, haue ſo terrible iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, how moche more he whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che when he is in ſynne, preſumeth
<pb facs="tcp:8976:60"/> to attayne to our Lordes bodye dothe get to hym ſelfe iudgement. Therfore let vs make cleane our ſelues frome all filthynes, and ſo let vs come to the holy thinges that we eſcape the iudgemente of them that put our Lord to death.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>Gycrilius ſuper Ioh. lib. iiii. cap. xiii</head>
            <p>WHen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Capharnytes whiche perceaued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of godly vertues of our Sauiour, by mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of tokens, ſhoulde gladely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue his ſermon, and yf any thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſemyd harde they humblye ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulde haue deſyered the ſolucion of them,<note place="margin">To aſk this que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how is a Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es word</note> but they allway do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſayinge: how can he geue vs his fleſhe? they cryed together of God with greate wyckedneſſe, nor it came to their myndes that
<pb n="liiii" facs="tcp:8976:60"/> nothinge is impoſſible with God. For when they were carnall (as Paule ſaithe) they coulde not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſpirituall thinges. But let vs I beſeche you take a enſam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple at the ſynnes of others, and puttinge ſure faith to myſteryes, euer in ſo high thinges this worde how: Let vs eyther thinke or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, for this is a Iewes worde, and the cauſe of extreme tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Therfore Nicodemus when he ſayde: how can this thinge be done? he harde worthely. Arte thou a maſter in Iſrael, and kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt not theſe thinges? Therfore we being taught by the faute of other when God worketh, let vs not aſke how. But let vs graunte to hym onely the waye of knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage of his owne worke. For as thoughe none knew what god is after nature, yet by faith he
<pb facs="tcp:8976:61"/> iuſtified, when he beleueth hym to geue rewardes to them that ſeke hym. So though he knew not the maner of his workes, when yet by fayth he doubteth not hym to be able to do all thinges, he getteth rewardes of this goodnes, not to be contempned. For our Lorde by Eſaye repreſſeth vs ſayinge: My counſayles be not as yours, nor my wayes as yours: As the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens be exalted from the earth, ſo be my wayes exalted from youre wayes, and my thoughtes from your thoughtes. Be not they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy greate tormentes, which do ſo contempne God the maker of all thinges, that they dare in his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ſaye howe? whom Scripture hath taught that he is able to do all thinges. O thou Iewe, howe cryeſt thou alſo now, this is foliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: I alſo gladly folowyng, wyll
<pb n="lv" facs="tcp:8976:61"/> aſke the, how dyddeſt thou go out of Egypt? How was Moſes rodde turned into a ſerpent? How dydde waters goo into the nature of bloude? Howe dyd oure fathers e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape through the myddes of the ſeas, as by dry lande? Howe dydde welles of water fly out of a ſtone? Howe ſtode Iordane? How by one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly crye, dyd ſtronge Hierico fall? There be innumerable thinges,<note place="margin">Quomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do euerti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> totam dei ſcriptura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; eius o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtruit.</note> in the whiche yf they aſke howe, thou muſt nedes turne all ſcripture: wherfore it dyd rather behoue you to beleue Chriſt: and yf any harde thinge be ſene vnto you, to aſke of hym mekely, then lyke dronkards to crye out, how can he geue vs his fleſhe?</p>
            <p>In the ſame boke. Cap. xiiii.</p>
            <p>It behoueth fyrſt to ſtablyſh the rootes of fayth in thy mynde, and then to enquire theſe thinges that
<pb facs="tcp:8976:62"/> be for man to be enquired, for to teacheth Eſayas. Except ye beleue ye ſhall not vnderſtand. But they afore they dyd beleue, dyd importu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nately aſke, and for that cauſe our Lorde howe it myghte be done, dyd not diſcloſe. But vnto his diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciples beleuinge, he gaue the frag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes of breade ſayinge: <hi>Take and eate this is my bodye,</hi> and of the cuppe, <hi>Drinke ye of this all: this is the cup of my bloude</hi> Thou doeſt perceaue that vnto them enquyringe withoute fayth, he dyd not ſhewe the maner of the miſtery:<note place="margin">Chriſtus miſterium expoſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t credenti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bus, non infidelibus</note> But to them that beleued (and not aſkinge howe) he dydde expounde. Lette them here this, whiche wyll not yet by reaſon of pryde receaue Chriſtes fayth. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte ye eate the fleſh of the ſonne of man, and drinke his bloude, ye ſhall not haue lyfe in you. For thei cannot with ſanctifienge of a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="lvi" facs="tcp:8976:62"/> lyfe, be parteners of fayth, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che by myſticall bleſſynge hathe not receaued Ieſu Chriſte. For he is lyfe after nature whiche is got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten afore of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: But no leſſe doth his bodye quicken. For it is ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnſpeakeably to the ſonne of GOD, of whome all thinges be quickened. Therefore it is called his bodye, and is one with him.</p>
            <p>For after the incarnation, it is one, and abydeth one without deui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion at all. But onelye that the worde of the father,<note place="margin">The word of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father and the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken of, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> virgin be not in natur one thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</note> and the temple taken of the vyrgin be not in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture one thynge. For man taken is not of the ſame ſubſtaunce with the worde of GOD, yet one with it, in a communication in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable. Howe than? the fleſſhe of oure Sauioure to the worde of God, whiche is naturallye lyfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge ioyned, is made lyuely when
<pb facs="tcp:8976:63"/> we eate it, then haue we lyfe. Not onely to the worde alway: but alſo touchinge often tymes. Our Lord Ieſus dyd rayſe deade men, as we reade. Luke .vii. that he myghte ſhewe his bodye alſo to be able to geue lyfe: that if by his onely tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge, corrupt thinges were made hoole agayne, how ſhal not we liue whiche both taſte, and eate that fleſhe? for he wyll alwaye reforme to his immortalitie the parteners of hym.<note place="margin">Deſyre not thou Iewe to aſk how</note> Nor deſyre not thou Iew, to aſke howe: but remember, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ugh water be naturally colde, yet by the comminge to of fyre, forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge his coldenes, it doth ſcalde. This ſame way alſo we, thoughe our nature be corruptible, yet by partakinge of lyfe, (beinge called from our wyckednes to the proper tye of it) we be faſhyoned agayne to lyfe. He that eateth Chriſtes
<pb n="lvii" facs="tcp:8976:63"/> fleſhe, hath lyfe euerlaſtynge. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="N"/> For the fleſhe hath the worde of God, that is lyfe eternall naturallye. Therefore he ſayth: I wyll rayſe hym vp in the laſte day. I he ſayd: that is, my body that ſhalbe eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I wyll rayſe vp hym. For he is not another thinge, but his owne fleſh. I ſaye not that, that by nature he is another thinge: but that after his incarnation, he doth not ſuffer him ſelfe to be deliuered into two ſonnes. I therfore ſayth he, whiche am made man by fleſhe, wyll in the laſt daye rayſe them vp that eate me. My fleſſhe is very meate, and my bloude is very drinke. Chriſte maketh a difference here betwene the miſticall benediction, and Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na: and the riuers of waters oute of the ſtone, and the commynge of the holy cuppe. Thei did not bring eternall lyfe: but a ſhorte remedye
<pb facs="tcp:8976:64"/> of hunger. But the holy bodye of Chriſt is noryſhynge meate to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie, and lyfe eternall. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore we be the body and members of Chriſt, becauſe by this bleſſinge of the miſtery, we do take the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raye ſonne of God.</p>
            <p>He that eateth my fleſhe. &amp;c. For as muche as it is an harde thynge, and by faith rather then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes. He is receaued manye and dyuerſe wayes, he expoundeth the maruelouſe profight of it conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the foundation &amp; ground to be faith,<note place="margin">Exemplu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de cord, Vnum cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pus Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtoſumus. Eodem lib cap. <hi>19</hi>
               </note> as yf one dyd put to mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wax other wax, he muſte nedes mengle the one with the other. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo if one receaue the fleſh and bloud of our Lord, he muſt be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, that Chriſte be founde in hym and he in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This is the bread that came doun from heauen, ſurely they be great
<pb n="lviii" facs="tcp:8976:64"/> thinges, whiche be done of greate men. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="N"/> Therfore thoſe thinges that be geuen of Chriſt, is breade frome heauen: for it geueth to the eaters euerlaſtynge lyfe. A greate ſigne of the Godhead in his bodye ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye nature to inhabite. For theſe thinges be therfore geuen whiche paſſe al other nature. And therfore they of the rude ſorte be leſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued: but the moſt riche nature ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth greateſt riches, whiche Paul alſo merueilinge cryeth. The eye hath not ſene, nor the eare hath not hard, nor into many hath not come thoſe thinges whiche God hath or deined to them that loue him. Let vs not therfore miſſe here only the wordes of Chriſt, but let vs geue credit to him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teacheth vs faith, for els we ſhalbe vexed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the myſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beleuers. Ieſus knowinge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they murmered by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that many
<pb facs="tcp:8976:65"/> whiche folowed Chriſt, not percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge his wordes, were trobled, they thought thei were called of Chriſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cruell maners of wilde beaſtes, and to be ſtyred, that they ſhoulde eate the rawe fleſhe of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and drinke the bloude, whiche to heare is horrible. For as yet they dyd not know of this miſtery the forme and moſte Godly diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. They thought how the fleſh of this man coulde gyue eternall lyfe: but he, vnto whoſe eyes all thinges were naked and ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dothe by another marueylouſe thinge, bringe them to faith, you be (ſaith he), troubled in vayne for my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. What, and if ye do not beleue lyfe to be geuen to you in my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye? what will ye do when ye ſhall ſe me aſcende vp to heauen? what will ye ſaye then ſeyng that? will not that be a greate argument of
<pb n="lix" facs="tcp:8976:65"/> youre madneſſe? If ye do thinke that my fleſhe is not able to geue you lyfe, howe ſhall it aſcende into heauen as a byrde? howe ſhall it fly through the ayer? This in like maner is vnpoſſible to mankinde. If ſo be that my fleſhe agaynſt nature, ſhall aſcende to heauen, what letteth, that alſo agaynſte nature it maye quicken. For he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> made this earthely body heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he alſo made it quicknynge. thoughe by the nature of it ſelfe, it be corruptible. But remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber agayne Chriſt to be one, and not two, as many do foliſhly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme. Conſyder I ſay, that euery where after incarnacion he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hym ſelfe to be inuiſible.<note place="margin">Super Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hannem.</note> The ſprite it is that quickenyth, the fleſhe dothe nothing profight at all, though the nature of fleſh (as it is fleſhe) cannot quicken yet it
<pb facs="tcp:8976:66"/> maye do this, be cauſe it hathe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo greate operation of the worde, for it is a bodye, not of euery man, whoſe fleſhe can any thinge proſight. For not of Paul or Peter or of others: But of the veray lyfe, and the bodye of our Sauiour Ieſu Chriſt, into whiche the fulnes of the Godhead dothe inhabite maye do it. For ſeynge that hony is naturally ſwete, it maketh them ſwete, with whome it is myngled. Wolde it not be a folyſhe thinge to beleue the lyuely nature of the worde, not to geue to man in whome it dwellith, a vertu of quickenynge? For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe of Chriſt becauſe in it the onely ſonne of God dwelleth, maye alone quicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For he calleth hym ſelfe a ſprite. For God is a ſprite. And how the ſprite quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyth: we can neither vnderſtande,
<pb facs="tcp:8976:66"/> nor with tonge expreſſe. But by ſcilence and ſure faithe we do take that. What doth Chriſt promyſe? what dothe he bringe to beleuers? Surely no corruptible thinge, but a beſechinge whiche we get by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating of Chriſtes bodye and bloude, wherby we maye be brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght hole to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> incorrupcion. For it is a bodye of veray lyfe, retayninge in it the vertue of the worde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate. And full in power of hym, wherby all thinges do lyue and be: whiche thinges ſeynge they be ſo, let men baptyſed and beinge made partenars of the godly grace. Though they go to the Churche more ſeldome and by longe ſpace of tymes for a clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked religion, refuſe to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate miſtically Chriſt, they do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe them ſelues farre frome eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall lyfe, for ſouche refuſynge
<pb facs="tcp:8976:67"/> though it ſeme to come of religion it both cauſeth offence, and layeth ſnares, wherfore it behoueth with all ſtrengthes, to be clenſyd from ſynne, and foundacions of good ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing, ſette with great confidence to ronne, to take lyfe and pleaſure of the fleſhe, by continencye ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, that we go to the heauenly grace, that we be made partenars of the body of Chriſt. For ſo ſhall we chaſe awaye the deuill, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge partenars of the godly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, maye aſcende vnto lyfe and incorruptible.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Certayne ſayinges of Theophilactus .viii.c.lxiii. vpon the xxvi of Math.</head>
            <p>THey eatinge, Ieſus toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> breade, and ſet it to the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that he might ſhew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cruelty
<pb n="lxi" facs="tcp:8976:67"/> of Iudas. For at the table &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the meates of it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he if he had not ben a wilde beaſt, ſhoulde haue ſhewed hym ſelfe more tame then he, neither whan he was reproued vnderſtode. But taſtinge his bodye he dyd not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, for ſaying <hi>this is my body,</hi> he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that the bodye of our Lorde is breade, whiche is ſanctifyed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alter, and not an anſweringe fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure.<note place="margin">Non eſt fi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gura ſed corpus</note> For he ſayde not this is a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure. But <hi>this is my bodie.</hi> For it is tranſformed by an vnſpeakeable operacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea though it ſeme to vs breade, for we be weake,<note place="margin">Panis uide<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, ſed ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ro eſt,</note> and feare to eate rawe fleſhe, chefely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe of a man. Therfore dothe breade appere, But it is fleſhe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Super Marc. cap. xiiii.</head>
               <p>Whan Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt had bleſſed he brake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breade, and that do we alſo, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge therto prayers ſaynge: This
<pb facs="tcp:8976:68"/> is my body. This that I do geue, and you now take. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="L"/> For the breade is not only a figure of our Lordes bodye: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> but it is turned into our Lordes body. For he ſayth: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread that I wyll geue, is my fleſhe. He ſayd not, it is a figure of my fleſh: but it is my fleſhe. And howe ſaith he,<note place="margin">Cur earo non uide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> is not fleſhe ſene? Oh man for oure infirmitie this is done. For breade and wyne be of thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges wherewith we be accuſtomed withall. Them we do not abhorre: but bloude and fleſhe ſet forth, we beholdynge coulde not beare, but ſhoulde abhorre. Therfore the mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifull God condeſcending to oure infirmitie,<note place="margin">Tranſele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentatio</note> doth kepe the forme or kynde of breade and wyne: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vertu of fleſhe and bloude he chaungeth them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Super Iohannem. Cap. vi.</head>
               <p>Take that the breade that is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="lxii" facs="tcp:8976:68"/> of vs in miſteries, is not onely a certayne figuringe of our lordes fleſhe: but the very fleſh. For it is tranſformed by ſecrete wordes.</p>
               <p>That breade by a miſticall bleſſing and comming of the holy goſte,<note place="margin">Tranſfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>matio.</note> is chaunged into the body and bloud of Chriſt. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> And how ſayeſt thou? the fleſhe appeareth not to vs, but breade, that we ſhulde not abborre the eatinge of it. For if fleſh ſhuld haue appeared, we ſhoulde haue ben vnſemelye mynded agaynſte the communion: but now our lord condeſcendinge to our infirmitie, appeareth to vs in ſuche miſticall meat, as we haue ben accuſtomed to. The Iewes when they harde of the eatinge of his fleſhe, dydde miſbeleue, and therfore they ſpake a word of infidelitie, that is: How? For when the thoughtes of myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleiffe entered into the harte,
<pb facs="tcp:8976:69"/> then entered alſo how. Wherefore, he wyllynge to ſhew that it is not impoſſible, but very neceſſary: and that lyfe can none otherwyſe be had, except ye eate my fleſhe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Leo in his .xl. Epiſtle.</head>
            <p>LEt thoſe phantaſtical Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans tell me, what body Ieſus brought into the ſight of his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, the gates beynge ſhut?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Anſelmne Byſhoppe of Canterbury, almoſt fyue hundred yeares paſte, ſayeth vppon theſe wordes.</head>
            <p>This is my body. It appeareth vnto the vtter ſenſes of man to be but breade. But know ye by the ſences of the mynde, bycauſe (ſaith Chriſt) this is my body, none other but that ſame in ſubſtaunce, which ſhalbe geuen to death vpon the
<pb n="xliii" facs="tcp:8976:69"/> croſſe, and crucified for you.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Ll"/> Oure Lordes body is conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the ſigne of the Croſſe, &amp; the fount of baptiſme is hallowed and alſo preiſtes are made by the ſame ſigne. <hi>Aug. in pſal. xxxiii.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Haymo. Homil, paſsione Chriſti. Math. li.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> The breade is chaunged into our Lordes fleſhe, and the wyne into his bloude, not by a fygure, nor by a ſhadowe, but by the veritie.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Damaſcen in his .iiii. boke of the ryght catholyke faith, The .iiii. Chapter.</head>
            <p>Doeſt thou aſke of me howe breade is made Chriſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? and wine and water his bloud? I aunſwer vnto the: that the holy gooſt worketh theſe things aboue mans vnderſtandynge: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> but the breade and wyne are turned. The
<pb facs="tcp:8976:70"/> bodye is ioyned vnto the deitye, whiche body is of the virgin, not that the bodye taken of the virgin, commyth downe frome heauen: but that the breade it ſelfe and wyne are chaunged into the bodye and bloude of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> The bread wyne &amp; water through inuocation and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge of the holy goſte vnto them, are aboue nature chaunged into Chriſtes bodye and bloude, and they are not two bodyes, but one and the ſame bodye. The breade and wyne be not a figure onely of Chriſtes bodye and bloude. God forbyd, but the bodye and Bloude of Chriſt. Doſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſe breade? doſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſe wyne? do they auoyde beneth as other meates do? God forbyd. Thinke not ſo: for as wax if it be put once into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyer, no ſubſtaunce re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth, nothinge is lefte, ſo here
<pb n="xliiii" facs="tcp:8976:70"/> alſo thinke thou y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſteryes be conſumed by the ſubſtaunce of the bodye</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Damaſen lib. iiii. ca. xiiii.</head>
               <p>For as moch as our Lord is the ſpirituall Adam, it hath be ſemed mannes natiuite to be ſpirituall. And alſo his meate natiuite is geuen to vs by water and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſprite through holy baptizme (I ſaye) and the meate breade of lyfe. Our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt whiche came doune from heauen. For he was aboute to ſuffer for vs volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarye deathe, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nyght whiche he offred his owne ſelfe. He dyd diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a new teſtament to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Apoſtelles, &amp; by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all others beleuing in hym. In the parlor of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy and gloriouſe Syon eatinge the olde paſſouer with his diſciples, &amp; fulfillinge the olde teſtament. He waſhed
<pb facs="tcp:8976:71"/> his Diſciples fete, gyuinge them a token of holy baptiſme.</p>
               <p>Afterwarde breakinge breade he gaue to them ſaying. <hi>Take eate this is my bodye, whiche for you ſhalbe broken in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſion of ſynnes.</hi> In like maner ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng the cupe of wyne and water. gaue to them ſayeng. <hi>Drynke of this all. This is my bloude of the newe Teſtament whiche ſhalbe ſhed for you in remiſsion of ſynnes Do ye this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n remembraunce of me.</hi> For how often ſo euer ye ſhall eate this breade, and drinke this cuppe, ye ſhall ſhewe the death of our Lord, and confeſſe his reſurrection vntil he come. If the worde of God be a lyuynge thinge, and of efficacite. And all thinges that our Lorde woulde, he dyd? If he ſayde, let the lyght be made, and it was made? Be the fyrmamente made, and it was made. If by the worde of God the heauens were made, and with
<pb n="lxv" facs="tcp:8976:71"/> the ſprite of his mouth euery ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of them? If heauen and earth, water, fyer, and ayer, and al the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of them, by the worde of our lorde be made perfight, &amp; man him ſelf an expreſſed beaſt?<note place="margin">Vis uerbi dei conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuo manet</note> If god hym ſelfe a wylling worde be made man, and of the moſt pure and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled bloude of the holy vyrgyn, and in him ſelfe without ſeed haue ſuſteyned fleſhe? Can not he make breade his bodye, and wyne and water his bloude?<note place="margin">Argumen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nori.</note> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> He ſayde in the begynninge: let the earth brynge forth grene graſſe, and euen vntyll nowe after rayne it bringeth forth fruites beinge helped and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with Goddes worde. For god ſayde. <hi>This is my body, and this is my bloude,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoc Sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> continuo fiet denec ueniat.</note> 
                  <hi>and this do in remembraunce of me.</hi> And by the almyghty precepte of God vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll he ſhall come it is done, for as all thinges that God dyd, the holy
<pb facs="tcp:8976:72"/> gooſt workinge he dydde. And ſo nowe by the operation of the holy gooſte, theſe he doth aboue nature, whiche nothinge but onely fayth can take. Howe ſhall this be done to me ſaith the holy vyrgin, for I knowe not manne? The Aungell aunſwered. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> The holye gooſte ſhall come vpon the, and the vertue of the higheſt ſhall ouerſhadowe the. And nowe aſketh thou,<note place="margin">Quomo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>do.</note> howe is breade made the body of Chriſt? &amp; wyne and water the bloude of Chriſt? Euen to this I aunſwere the, The holy gooſte ſhadoweth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen theſe workes aboue ſpeache and vnderſtandinge. For the bread and wyne be chaunged, for GOD knowynge mans infirmitie doth tourne awaye,<note place="margin">Tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tatio.</note> and not beare many thinges that be not commen in vſe. Therfore he doth by his acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, vſe thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="lxvi" facs="tcp:8976:72"/> whiche be aboue nature,<note place="margin">Aquaeo unctio gratiae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritus ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctis rege<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neratio</note> by thinges accuſtomed to nature. And as in baptiſme becauſe it is a cuſtome to men to be waſſhed, and anoynted with oyle, be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the oyle and water, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of the holy goſte, and made it a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of regeneration, after the ſame maner (becauſe it is the maner to men,<note place="margin">F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corpi ſuum.</note> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> to eate bread and drink wine) he ioyned to theſe ſame his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, and made them his body and his bloud that be accuſtomed thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and whiche are aboue nature: That we maye be placed in thoſe thinges that be aboue nature. For the bodye after the trueth, is coyioyned to the godheade, that of the holy virgin is the bodye, not that the bodye (ye takinge) came downe from heauen: but that the breade and wyne is chaunged into the bodye and bloude of God.
<pb facs="tcp:8976:73"/> And if thou doſte require the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how it is done? Let it be yno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wgh for the to hear that it is done by the holy goſte. Euen as of the holy virgin mother of God with hym ſelfe, and in hym ſelfe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ſuſteyned fleſhe, and nothing elſe knowe we but that the worde is trew, pytthy, and allmighty. But the maner is vnſpeakeable, and vnſerchable, nor it is not redy that to be tolde, how naturally by ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge of breade, and wyne and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by drynkinge into the bloude of the eater and drinker, ſhoulde be chaunged and made a nother body, beſydes that, that it was of hym. Euen ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breade of ſettinge forthe, and wyne and water by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation and commynge of the holy goſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> ſupernaturally is chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into the bodye and bloude of Chriſt, &amp; they be not two but one.
<pb n="lxvii" facs="tcp:8976:73"/> Therfore it is done to them that take it in faith worthely in remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſynnes, and eternall lyfe, and for the kepynge of the ſoule and the bodye. But to them that in myſbeleue vnworthely do take, they take it to ponyſhment and payne.<note place="margin">Morcebri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſti.</note> Euen as Chriſtes deathe to the beleuers is made lyfe and incorruptibilite into the fruction of eternall bleſſednes. But to the infideles and murderars of Chriſt to torment an euerlaſtyng payne <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="L"/> The breade and wyne is not a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the bodye and bloude of Chriſt (God forbyd:<note place="margin">Non eſt fy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gura.</note>) but it is the body of our Lorde deifyed. The ſame Lorde ſaying: this is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, not a figure of my bodye, but my bodye, and not a figure of my bloude, but my bloude. And therefore this be ſaide to the Iewes: Excepte ye eate the fleſh
<pb facs="tcp:8976:74"/> of the ſonne of man, and drinke his bloude, ye ſhall not haue lyfe eternall. My fleſhe verely is meate, and my bloude verely is drynke, and afterwarde he ſaithe: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> he that eateth me, ſhall lyue for me. Therfore with all fear &amp; pure conſcience and vndoutynge fayth, let vs come, and let it allwaye be to vs as we beleue, not doutyng, and let vs worſhyppe hym with all clennes of mynde and bodye. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Ll"/> Let vs come to hym with bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge deſyre,<note place="margin">Manus in modu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis forma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes.</note> formyng our ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des after the faſhion of the croſſe, and let vs take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodye of Chriſt crucified. Melchiſedech toke bread and wyne to Abraham commyng frome the killinge of ſtraungers whiche was the preiſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higheſt God.<note place="margin">Figur chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſti Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedech.</note> That table prefigured this miſticall table, as that preiſt of Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true preiſt afore hym hath
<pb n="lxviii" facs="tcp:8976:74"/> prefigured the figure and image.<note place="margin">
                     <p>Panis pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pitiationis.</p>
                     <p>Hoſtia in cruenta</p>
                  </note> This breade did the ſhew breades figure, this is a pure hoſt bloude<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les, whiche frome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne ryſynge to the ſittinge, whiche the Lorde ſpeaketh by the prophet, to be offered vnto hym: That is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodye and bloude of Chriſt,<note place="margin">&amp;</note> for a ſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of our ſoule and bodye, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſumed, vncorrupt,<note place="margin">Non in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſum iens</note> not goynge frome the bodye as other meate (God forbyd that) but into your ſubſtaunce and conſeruation. Let vs with all vertu awayte, that we take not parte in the partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacion of heretikes, nor geue:<note place="margin">Heretici ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtinatiam fugiamus</note> For do ye geue holy thinges to dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges? that we be not made parte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of their error and euyll faith and condemnation. For we be all one bodye, bycauſe we participate of one breade. They be called alſo exemplaries of thinges to come. Not as not trwely beynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodye
<pb facs="tcp:8976:75"/> and bloude of Chriſt, but by cauſe now by them we participate the diuinitie of Chriſt, and then intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectually by onely viſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Euſebius Emiſſenus Anno. ccxciiii.</head>
               <p>In as moche as he was aboute to take awaye his aſſumptid bodye from their eyes, and to brynge it in emonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſterres. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> It was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſary y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the day of his ſupper he ſhoulde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrate to vs a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his bodye &amp; bloude, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he myght be contynually worſhypped by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery whithe was once offered for a pryce: and that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daiely &amp; neuer ceaſſynge redemption whiche dyd ronne for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> helth of all, ſhoulde be a perpetuall oblation of redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, that euerlaſtynge ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation myght lyue in memorye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; alwaye preſent in grace, one true and perfight hooſte, to be eſtemyd
<pb n="lxix" facs="tcp:8976:75"/> in faith, not in forme, not to be iudged by exterior loue. Wherfore the heauenly auctorite confyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth: for my fleſh is veray meate, and my bloude is veray drynke. Awaye therfore with all doute of infidelitie. For he that is the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the gyfte, is alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wytneſſe of the truthe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> For he conuerteth the viſible creatures by his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete power, into the ſubſtaunce of his bodye &amp; bloude in his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſaying thus. Take ye &amp; eate ye this is my bodye: &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge repetyd. Take &amp; drinke, this is my bloud. Therfore as at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynteme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our Lorde, commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſodenly, &amp; of nawght ſtode vp the highthes of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depeneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flouds, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> largenes of thearth: So by lyke power in ſpirituall ſacramentes, where power co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effect ſeruith. How greate &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:8976:76"/> howe muche honorable benefites doth the ſtrength of the deuine bleſſinge worke? How ſhuld it not be vnto you a newe thinge, and im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſſible? that earthly and mortall thinges maye be turned into the ſubſtaunce of Chriſt? Aſke thyne owne ſelfe whiche arte regenerate in Chriſt, lately thou was a ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger from lyfe, a ſtraunger from mercy, and from the way of helth. Inwardelye thou beynge deade, was outlawed, ſodenly beynge en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered within the lawes of Chriſte, and made newe throughe holſome miſteries, into the body of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. Not by ſeing, but by beleuing thou haſte ouerpaſſed. And of the ſonne of perdition haſte deſerued by pryuy clemency to be made the elected ſonne of God, abydinge in a viſible meaſure, arte made grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter than thy ſelfe inuiſible<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="lxx" facs="tcp:8976:76"/> augmentinge, when thou was the ſelfe ſame thinge. Muche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wayes was thou in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedinge of fayth, nothinge is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to in the outwarde parte, and all is chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged in the inward part. And yf manne beynge made the ſonne of Chriſt, and Chriſt beynge formed in the mynde of manne: as therefore withoute corporall ſence, the olde wylynes put down, thou haſte ſodenlye put on a newe dignitie. And as in that, that GOD hath cured in the thinges hurte. He hath waſſhed thynges infected, he hathe wyped awaye thinges defiled. They be not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytte to thyne eyes, but to thy wittes. And when thou goeſte vp to the alter to be filled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpiritual meats, behold (yea, with thy faith) <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> a ſacramente, the body and bloude of God, honoure, meruell, towche
<pb facs="tcp:8976:77"/> with thy minde, take it with thy hande of thy harte, and moſt of all take a hole drawght of the inward man.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>S. Hierom in his .iii. boke againſt the Pellagians ſayth.</head>
                  <p>Chriſt taught his apoſtels that they beleuinge, ſhould be bolde to ſaye daylye in the ſacrifice of his body, the Pater noſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>S. Barnard in feſto Martini. Anno dom. M.xiii.</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/> The very ſubſtaunce of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes fleſh is now alſo preſent with vs no doute truelye, but in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the alter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Rupert in the, vi. chapt. of Ihon. Anno domini. M.xiii.</head>
                  <p>This is our Lordes body which dyd hange vpon the croſſe, &amp; this is his bloude that was ſhedde out for all the worlde.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="lxxi" facs="tcp:8976:77"/>
               <head>Hugo in annotationibus in, i. corinth. xi. queſt. xcix. Anno. M ccc,xxxiiii.</head>
               <p>It is knowen vnto the faythfull perſon,<note place="margin">&amp;</note> that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtaunce of bread paſſeth into the bodye, and wyne into the bloude. As Chriſt ſaying: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> Take, this is my body, dydde then chaunge by his worde that breade and wyne into his very bodye and bloude. Euen ſo do we vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly beleue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> that the wordes ſayde of a preiſt by that order, and with the ſame intent that Chriſt ſayd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, do chaunge the breade and wyne into Chriſtes very bodye, and his very bloude.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Bruno. Anno dom. M.C, lii.</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> This thinge whiche was a lyttell before breade, is now verely my bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye, whiche bodye ſhalbe geuen to death for you, althoughe I nowe wyll geue to you immortall, and not apte to ſuffer. He ſpeaketh in
<pb facs="tcp:8976:78"/> the perſon of Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ioannes Gerſon. Anno. <hi>M.</hi>cccc.xxix.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> We muſt ſay that albeit Chriſte is vnderneth the kinde of bread &amp; wyne, but yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread paſſeth into chriſtes body, &amp; wine into his blod.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Oecumenius whiche was a greke in his .x. Epiſt. vnto the Heb.</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> The Apoſtell Paule would not haue ſayde, thou arte a preiſt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of that oblation and hoſt, or ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice which is once made: but he ſayd it, hauing a reſpect to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes which be now a daies, by who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me as meanes, Chriſt maketh ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice, and is offered in ſacrifice, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che taught them alſo in the miſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſupper, the maner of ſuch a ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice. And further we make a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of one, and the ſame Chriſtes death, and we eate at al tymes one body of Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Sedulius whiche was .M.c.xix. paſt writeth thus.</head>
                  <pb n="lxxii" facs="tcp:8976:78"/>
                  <p> Beware y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye eate not the body vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worthely, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> whiles it is chriſtes body</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Gregory Emiſſene which was aboue .M.c. yeares paſt.</head>
                  <p>The inuiſible preiſt (Chriſt) tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth the viſible creatures of bread and wine, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> by his worde and ſecrete power into the ſubſtaunce of his body and blud, thus ſaying: Take and eate, this is my body. And far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſaith: it is Chriſtes fleſhe which we do receaue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t couered with the forme of bread, &amp; his bloud which we drink, vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kind of apeara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; ſauor of wyne.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Rabanus. Lib. i. in Exodum.</head>
               <p>What auayleth it to receaue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy mouth Chriſtes body &amp; bloud, And to do againſte hym with all euell maners?</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Nicolaus de Lyra, which was about .vc.xxxiii. yeres paſt.</head>
                  <p>Theſe wordes that I ſpake, ſayth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8976:79"/> Chriſt. Iohn .vi. are ſprite &amp; lyfe. But yet this ſpiritually is not ſo vnderſtande ſayth Lyre, or ſo to be taken, that Chriſtes fleſh ſhuld be in the ſacrament of the aulter onely as a ſigne, lyke as certayne heretikes haue ſayd, for it is there really. But becauſe Chriſtes fleſhe is eaten in this ſacrament after a certayne ſpirituall manner, in as muche as the viſible kyndes are rent with the teeth, and eaten: and mannes ſpirite the ſoule is refreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed therby, through the power of God knit vnto the fleſhe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Damaſus Epiſtola ad Stephanum. Anno dom. viii.c.lxx.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> Let not any man lightly agre in backbytinge or accuſyng, or con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dempning of their brethren Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and whiche alſo do make Chriſtes bodye with their owne mouthe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="lxxiii" facs="tcp:8976:79"/>
               <head>Athanaſius. Lib. de paſsione imaginis Chriſti. cap. vii. Anno dom. ccclxxix.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> It is not otherwyſe to be iudged of euery catholyke perſon, beſides that whiche is written of vs, as thoughe ſome thinges mighte be found in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world of Chriſtes fleſh: but that whiche is dayly made v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the aulter, ſpirituallye by the prieſtes handes.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Felix martyr. almooſt a .M.ccc. yeares paſt.</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> It was not ſemely that they whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che do dayly make Chriſtes bodye with their owne proper mouthe, ſhuld ſuffer ſo great perſecution.</p>
                  <p>The counſell of Laterane, in the whiche were aſſembled .M.ccc.xv. learned men, which determined the preſence of Chriſt to be in the ſacrament of the aulter.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8976:80"/>
                  <p>There is one vniuerſall church of the faithfull without which no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vtterly is ſaued: in whiche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame preiſt him ſelfe (Ieſus Chriſt) is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice, whoſe body and bloude is truely contained in the ſacrament of the aulter, vnderneth the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of bread &amp; wyne: and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of breade and wyne, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the bodye and bloude of Chriſt, through goddes power. The determination of the hole vniuerſitie of Paris, in the time and raygne of kynge Frauncis.</p>
                  <p>Euery Chriſten man is bounde to beleue ſtedfaſtly, that in the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecration of the Sacramente, the breade and wyne are turned into the very body and bloud of Chriſt, the kyndes and formes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breade and wyne onely remayninge. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneth the which, the very bodye
<pb n="lxxiiii" facs="tcp:8976:80"/> of Chriſt is really (or in very dede) <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/> contayned, which was borne of the vyrgin, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> and hath ſuffered vppon the croſſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ The ſayinges of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyn Luther in his boke intituled, the chief articles of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian fayth.</head>
            <p>Of the ſacrament of the alter hold we, that breade and wyne at the ſupper, is the very body &amp; bloude of Chriſt. And is not onelye mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred and receiued of the rightous, but alſo of wicked chriſtians.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the ſame.</head>
               <p>Except that they before dyd alter and falſely interpretate gods wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des and ordinaunce, as the preſent enemies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrament do, whiche would in very dede haue nothinge but breade and wyne, becauſe they haue not alſo the wordes and ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunce
<pb facs="tcp:8976:81"/> inſtituted of god: but haue peruerted and altered the ſame af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter their fantaſy. In the ſame.</p>
               <p>For euen ther is in this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie: and where as ſhe is remiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of ſynnes, that is a kinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of grace and of right pardon. For ther is the goſpell, baptiſme, and the ſacrament of the Alter, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="O"/> wherin remiſſion of ſynnes is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, gyuen, and receaued, and euen ther is alſo Chriſt and his ſprite and God. And yet Luther is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempned as an erityke, becauſe he wolde haue bread to be Ioyned with the body, whiche is contrary to the catholyk churche.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Melancton.</head>
               <p>Saynt Ambros wold neuer haue traueled, (ſayth Melancton vnto Oecolampadius) ſo many mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles as he doth ſpeake of this mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, to the declarynge of goddes
<pb n="lxxv" facs="tcp:8976:81"/> omnipotencye: and he had not thought, the nature of breade to be chaunged in this myſtery.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Eraſmus Rothoroda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus vnto Coradus Pellicanus in his Epiſt. vi c.lxxvi. pag.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/> WHat maddnes were it for me yf I ſhoulde pronounce, that there is nothinge elſe in the ſacrament of the Alter, but onely breade &amp; wyne. I do acknowelege my ſelfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I were worthy of death if euer eny man harde this of me, either in earneſt or in boorde, that there is nothinge elſe in the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſacrament but onely breade and wyne: or that ther is not real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there preſent, the very bodye &amp; bloud of our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And farther he ſaithe: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Ff"/> ſaynte Paule dothe thinke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an Angell is not to be harde if he do preathe
<pb facs="tcp:8976:82"/> an other goſpell than the catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyke churche dothe approue and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea &amp; the ſame churche hathe perſwaded vnto me, to beleue, and to geue credence to the goſpell, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> &amp; by hyr inſtruction haue I euer learned how I ought to expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell, &amp; hitherto haue I euer worſhypped in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Chriſt which ſuffered death &amp; paſſion for me as all other trwe chriſtenyd men hath done. Nor yet hitherto, dyd I neuer ſe any thing wherefor I ought to go from this mynde and ſtedfaſt opynion. Nor <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Ff"/> no mans reaſonynge ſhalbe able to cary me awaye frome the holy ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and agrement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers of Chriſtes church. For thoſe eight wordes of Moyſes: in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge god made heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth, be of more ſtrengthe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gumentes &amp; reaſons of Ariſtotle
<pb n="lxxvi" facs="tcp:8976:82"/> and all other philoſophers.</p>
            <p>True it is, that the verye bodye of our Lorde and Sauiour Chriſt is there in the ſacrament, thoughe it be not to mans ſences or reaſon perceptible. But yet is that ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a pleage and wonderful me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of his ineſtimable loue towar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des vs, and a ſtedfoſt comfort wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by to ſtablyſh oure hope towarde God. The ſcripture doth make for vs. We haue theſe playne wordes in holy ſcripture: This is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy whiche is geuen for you. And this is my bloud which ſhalbe ſhed for you. Where do they fynd in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/> This is not my body? or this is but a figure, or ſigne, and token of my bodye.</p>
            <p>They ſhall neuer be able to bringe forth any place of the auncient do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors which ſhal by playne and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe wordes contayne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is
<pb facs="tcp:8976:83"/> not in the bleſſed Sacramente of the aulter, the very body &amp; bloude of our ſauiour Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I pray you what thinge is in this matter whiche moueth you thus highly to extoll this ſpiritual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing of the body &amp; bloud of our lorde in the ſacrament. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/> Wolde you therby perſwade vnto me that I ſhould not holde with the corporal eatinge and drinkinge of the ſame body and bloude of our Lord alſo? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Kk"/> And wold you by that menes that I ſhould now forſake the true do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, whiche the catholike church hath euer ſtill taught ſo manye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges together, one folowinge and ſuccedinge after another, to harke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto your newly inuented onelye ſpirituall eating and drinking of thoſe high miſteries, therby vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſecludinge the corporall eatinge and drinkinge of the ſame ſelf bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="lxxvii" facs="tcp:8976:83"/> Sacrament.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>Eraſmus in his epiſtle to Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaſar byſhop of Heldeſyn. pag. M.ccccc.lxxvii.</head>
            <p>And ſuerly there is nothing more effectuall to noriſh in oure mother holy churche a perfight and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſoluble concorde, than that the ſame oure mother the Catholyke churche, eatinge of one bodye, and drinkinge of one bloude, by one ſpirite is made and compacte into one bodye, by whom ſhe alſo recea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uinge life, is knit vnto our lyuing head Chriſt. And yet do we nowe ſe that all theſe great benefittes, and high promocions notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinge, how that through the fligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty craftes of oure deſaytefull and ſtronge aduerſarye Sathan, it is brought to paſſe, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame moſt beneficial gifte of the ſacramente of the body and bloud of our moſt
<pb facs="tcp:8976:84"/> mercyfull &amp; moſte te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derly louynge Sauiour, geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs to bringe all ꝑſons into vnite &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cord, hath ben the matter where vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in olde tyme ſo many diſcencions haue ryſyn, and of late yeares are now agayne renewed, while y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſome ther be whiche do deny that ther is any thinge elſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed ſacrament, but onely the outwarde tokyns of the body &amp; bloud of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. Some others do knowlege chriſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: but yet vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtance of bread and wine. And again ſome ther were y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſayde, how that through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of conſecration, the ſubſtaunce of breade and wyne do fyrſt periſhe, and ſo ſuccedeth after the bodye and the bloude of our Sauiour Chriſt. Some others do holde that our Sauiour by the wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſecration dothe become breade
<pb n="lxxviii" facs="tcp:8976:84"/> and wyne by their fantaſtical min<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, making it but a light matter that was once incarnate, and dyd for our ſakes become man. There haue alſo ben ſome that were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Starcoraniſte,<note place="margin">&amp;</note> whiche irreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent parſons deſerued well ſo vile a name, becauſe they both ymagin and ſpeake ſo vylye and withoute all reuerence of ſo highe a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente. The countreye of Grece alſo, to diſquiet the vnitie of the Catholyke Churche, hathe ſente forth amongeſte vs theyr leuay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſo called, becauſe they dare preſume contrarye to holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, to leue the vſe of pure bread vnlayuened, and do conſecrate in breade whiche is leuayned. And after he ſayth, woulde to GOD that ſuch perſons as haue folowed Berengarius in his maner of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng concerning the veritie of the
<pb facs="tcp:8976:85"/> body and bloude of our Sauiour Chriſt to be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed ſacrament of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Alter, whiche thinge he deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo to be, woulde in lyke wyſe folow hym in repentynge of theyr ſelues as he dyd: and that whiche now in our dayes be infected with the ſame erroure, wolde ſo vnyte them ſelues vnto the catholyke Churche as he dyd, whiche dyed for his offence, full ſore repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Farthermore ther hath ryſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute this bleſſed ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable queſtions. As how is the tranſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brought to paſſe? that is to ſaye: how dothe the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of breade geue place vnto the very ſubſtaunce of the bodye of our Sauioure Chriſt? Alſo how the accident of breade and wyne be preſerued, and do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne after theyr former ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauces be gone? And howe is it
<pb n="lxxix" facs="tcp:8976:85"/> that theſe accidentes do kepe ſtyll theyr color, theyr ſmel, their ſauor, and alſo haue power to fyll lyke other fode? All whiche qualy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes the breade and wyne had in them ſelues afore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate. Alſo at what moment the body &amp; bloude of Chriſt doth ſeace to be in the ſacrament? Alſo whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> formes be corrupted any other fubſtaunce do ſuccede? Alſo how that one ſelfe ſame body maye be at once in places innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable? Alſo whether the body of a perfight man maye be vnder ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle a broken peace of breade? And many ſuch other folyſh queſtions, which behoueth with ſoberneſſe to be entretyd of, amongeſt ſuche per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons as haue theyr wyttes exercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in diſputynge &amp; reaſonyng vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on ſouche high matters. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> But as vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laye people it dothe ſuffiſe
<pb facs="tcp:8976:86"/> that they do beleue, that after the wordes of conſecration be once by the miniſter ſpoken ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of bread and wyne, that ther is incontinent the very body &amp; bloud of our ſauiour chriſt, which nether can be deuided, nor yet receaue any hurt: nor is not mete to receue any maner of iniury, whatſoeuer chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces do become of the outward for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of bread and wyne. For if the ſacred body of our lorde ſhould be throwne into the myre, or into any vyle gonge, or any otherwiſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any irreuerent parſonnes, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge ſhould be iniured or ſoylde: in dede the mooſte iniury that can be done vnto it, is whan it is rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into the mouth of a wicked &amp; ſynfull parſon, whiche is ſore ſoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led &amp; ſpotted with greuouſe and odible ſinne. Now ſurely it is ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſittinge for our chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="lxxx" facs="tcp:8976:86"/> to entreat and order the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde formes of breade and wyne of the holy ſacrament with all due reuerence. But as concerning the very body of our Sauiour it ſelf: lyke as God after his nature, is no leſſe glorious in a vyle ſynke, than he is in heauen, and canne by no malyce of man, or chaunce by man, or otherwyſe happeninge, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue any hurt or iniurye, no more can the glorified body of our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſte, what iniurye ſoeuer be doone vnto the outewarde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of breade and wyne. And to be breife agaynſte all doubtes and ſeruples of mannes weake know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Lette vs fyrſt? call to oure myndes, the immeſurable power of God, vnto whome nothinge is impoſſible: yea &amp; vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther is nothing but it is light to be done, ſo it be his pleaſure, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhould ſo
<pb facs="tcp:8976:87"/> be (whiche ſaide) Take eate <hi>This is my bodye.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Aa"/> And in a nother place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Epiſtle he ſaithe: At y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe tyme the Angelicall ſprites do with moſte humble reuerence ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de a boute the Alter, ther to do there worſhippe, and lowly reuerence: he alſo is there preſent whome all the heauenly hooſtes of bleſſed ſprites do deſire to behold and loke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And a litle after: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Aa"/> Let all preiſtes therefore conſider the highnes of their profeſſion, whan they do ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d at the aulter, they haue aungels to miniſter vnto them. Theſe be the wordes of the famous clerke Eraſmus Rothorodame, whereby all Chriſtian people maye knowe what was his opinion in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, not diſagreing from the olde fathers here before written.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <pb n="lxxxi" facs="tcp:8976:87"/>
            <head>¶ Thomas Cramner in his Cathechiſme, in the .cc.xxxv. lefe, of the fyrſt ſyde.</head>
            <p>CHriſt ſayth of the breade, this is my bodye, and of the cuppe this is my bloude. Wherefore we ought to beleue that in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we receaue truely the bodye and bloud of Chriſt. For God is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and he is able therfore to do all thinges what he wyl. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore when Chriſt taketh bread and ſaith. Take, eate, this is my body, we oughte not to doubte, but we eate his very body. And whan he taketh the cuppe and ſaith. Take drinke this is my bloude, we ought to thinke aſſuredly that we drinke his very blode. And this we muſte beleue, yf we will be counted chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n men. And where as in this p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>illous tyme, certayne dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceytfull
<pb facs="tcp:8976:88"/> perſons be founde in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places, who of very frowardnes will not graunte that there is the body and bloude of Chriſte: but deny the ſame for none other cauſe but that they can not compaſſe by mannes blynde reaſone, howe this thinge ſhoulde be brought to paſſe. ye good children, ſhall with all diligence beware of ſuche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that ye ſuffer not youre ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to be deceaued by them. For ſuche men ſurely are not true Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians, neyther as yet haue they learned the firſte Article of the Crede, whiche teacheth that God is almyghtye, whiche ye good chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren haue already perfectlye lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, wherfore eſchew ſuche erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous opinions, and beleue the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of oure Lorde Ieſus, that you eate and drinke his verye bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e and bloude in the Sacrament, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe
<pb n="lxxxii" facs="tcp:8976:88"/> mannes reaſon cannot comprehende howe and after what maner the ſame is there preſent. Wherfore doubte not good chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but there is the bodye and bloude of our Lorde, whiche we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue in the lordes ſupper. For he hath ſayde ſo, and by the power of his worde hath cauſed it ſo to be. Wherefore ſeynge Chriſt ſayth: do this as often as ye do it in remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce of me, it is euident there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that Chriſte cauſeth, euen at this tyme, his bodye and bloude to be in the Sacrament, after the maner and faſſhion, as it was at that tyme, when he made his mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye with his diſciples. For elſe we coulde not do it in the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of hym, that is to ſaye: to receaue his bodye and bloud, euen ſo as he hym ſelfe dydde geue it to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s diſciples.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:89"/>
            <p>And let not the folyſſhe talke of vnbeleuers moue you, who are wonte to aſke this queſtion. How can the preiſte or miniſter make the bodye and bloude of Chriſt? To this I anſwere, that the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter dothe not this of hym ſelfe: But Chriſt hym ſelfe dothe gyue vnto vs his fleſhe and bloude, as his wordes dothe euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly declare.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the .cc.xxxiiii.</head>
               <p>And this is the meanynge and playne vnderſtandyng of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the Lordes ſupper. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for learne them diligently I praye you, that when ye be aſked, what is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio or the Lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per? ye maye anſwer, it is the true bodye &amp; true bloude of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt hymſelfe, to be eaten and dronken of vs Chriſten peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnder the forme of brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and wyne.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <pb n="lxxiii" facs="tcp:8976:89"/>
            <head>¶ In the fyrſte booke of common prayer, ſet forth by kynge Edwarde the ſyxt. fol. c.xvi.</head>
            <p>HEre vs (O mercifull father) we beſeche the, and with thy holy ſprite and worde vouchſafe to bleſſe and ſanctifye theſe thy gyftes of breade and wyne, that they maye be vnto vs the bodye and bloude of thy moſte dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louyd ſonne Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And in the .cxxi. lefe</head>
               <p>And ye muſte not thinke leſſe to be receaued in parte then in the hoole. But in euery of them the hole bodye of our ſauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:90"/>
            <head>¶ Of prayinge for the deade.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E liberal vnto al men liuinge: yet let not to do good euen vnto them that are dead. Ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſiaſticus .vii.</p>
            <p>Set thy bread and wyne vpon the burieng of the iuſt, and eate and drinke not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with ſynners. Tob. iiii.</p>
            <p>So he gathered of euery one a certayn, inſomuch that he brought together two, M. Dragmes of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer whiche he ſente vnto Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, that there might a ſacrifice be offered for the miſdeede. In the whiche place he dyd wel and right: for he had ſome conſideration and ponderinge of the lyfe that is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this tyme. For if he hadde not
<pb n="lxxxiiii" facs="tcp:8976:90"/> thoughte that they whiche were ſlayne, dyd yet lyue, it had ben ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluouſe and vayn, to make any vowe or ſacrifice for them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were deade. But forſomuche as he ſawe that they whiche dye in the fauour and beleife in God, are in good reſt and ioye, he thought it to be good and honorable for a reconſilynge, to do the ſame, for theſe that were ſlayne, that the offence mighte be forgeuen .ii. Machab. xii.</p>
            <p>Viſet the ſicke, bury the deade, and diligentlye do their exequis and diriges, and praye, and alſo geue almoſe for them. Saynt Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his compendiolo.</p>
            <p>We do ſcelebrate the daye of the departinge: for thoſe that ſeme to dye, do not dye. Therfore we reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſainctes our parents &amp; oure frendes. And we make a ſolempne memorye for them that dye in the
<pb facs="tcp:8976:91"/> faithe. And we reioyſe as well at their relefe: as alſo they deſye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe our Godly conſummation and ende in the faithe. And ſo we do not after that ſorte celebrate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye of the natiuitie, for they that dye (in the Lorde) ſhall lyue all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes. Origen in Iob.</p>
            <p>And whan thou haſte aſked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God for whoſe ſprit thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt mention of, &amp; for whom thou geueſt yearely oblations. &amp;c. <hi>Tertulian de exortacione caſtitatis pagi, ccccc.lxxxi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Geue reſt (O Lorde) to thy wel-beloued ſeruaunt Theodoſius, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen that ſame reſt that thou haſt prepared for thy ſaynctes that his ſoule turne thither from whenſe it deſcendyd. <hi>Ambroſius ſuper obitu The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſii imperatoris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some vſe to obſerue the daye of the buryall, ſome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde daye,
<pb n="lxxxv" facs="tcp:8976:91"/> ſome the .vii. day, ſome the .xxx. day and ſome the mon the daye, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery obſeruinge hath auctorite, by the whiche obſeruinge the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye offyce of godlynes is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled. <hi>Amb. in oratione ſuper obitu Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſii imperatoris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I commende vnto the, O Lorde God allmighty the innocent ſoule of my brother now deade. And I offer vnto the my Sacrifice, take mercifully, and gladely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſent or gyfte of a brother the ſacrifice of a preiſt. <hi>Amb. in oratione de obitu fratris ſui ſatiri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not to be denyed that ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of men departed are releued through the godlynes of their frendes alyue, when the ſacrifyce of our mediator Chriſt is offered for them, or elſe almoſe be geuen for them in the Churche. <hi>Aug. in his enchiridion. ca. ex. ad dulcimum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:92"/>
            <p>When the people ſhall ſtande holding vp their handes with the preiſt, and the dreadfull ſacrifice is ſet forth, ſhal we not optayne god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des fauour, praying for the deade? Aug. vpon the firſt chapter vnto the Hebrues,</p>
            <p>We muſte trauell as muche as maye be, that the deade may be hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pen, not with wepinge, but with prayer, ſupplications, almoſe, and ſacrifice. Aug. in his .xli. Homilie. i. Cor. xv.</p>
            <p>I Auguſtyne beſeche the O Lord, for the ſinnes of my mother. Here me by the mediſine of oure woundes which hange on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, and ſitting on thy right hand, and prayeth for vs, &amp;c. <hi>Auguſt. lib. confeſs. ix cap. xiii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thorough the prayers verely of holy churche, and thoroughe the holſome ſacrifice, and almes which
<pb n="lxxxvi" facs="tcp:8976:92"/> is geuen for the ſpirites of them, it is not to be douted the deade to be holpen, that it may with them be done more mercifull of the Lorde, then their treſpaſſes deſerued. This geuen of the fathers, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall churche obſerueth, that they that dye in the communion of the body and bloude of Chriſte, when they be remembred to that ſacrament, it is prayed for them, &amp; that is offered for them. <hi>Aug. ſermo. xxxii. oratio ſacrificium altaris &amp; eleemoſina proſint defunctis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſoules of good men depar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, are not ſeperated from the churche, or elſe a remembraunce of them ſhoulde not be made at gods Alter, in the communion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes Alter for them. <hi>Aug. de ciuitate dei. lib. xx. cap. ix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I did not wepe in thoſe prayers whiche we made to the (O Lorde)
<pb facs="tcp:8976:93"/> when the ſacrifice of oure price or redemption was offered for my mother Monica. <hi>Aug. lib. ix. confeſſionu. cap. xii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My mother Monica commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded vs not to do theſe thinges for her, but onely ſhe deſired a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of her to be made at thy aulter (O Lorde) whiche ſhe hadde dayly ſerued, from whiche aulter ſhe knew that the holy gooſt or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to be diſtributed, by whiche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> writing of our own hand (ſinne) that was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary vnto vs, is done away, by whiche hooſte or ſacrifice thy enemy the deuill is vainquiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed or ouercome. <hi>Aug. in Lib. ix. confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionum. Cap. xiii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When ſacrifice either of the aul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, or els of any manner of almoſe are offered for the dead which were baptiſed. They ar thankeſgeuing for them that be very good people
<pb n="lxxxvii" facs="tcp:8976:93"/> and for them whiche are not verye badde, they are propiciations, for purchaſinges of the mercy and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God. Eyther they do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit vnto this thinge, that it maye be full remiſſion, or elſe at the leaſt that the payne be made more tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable. <hi>Aug. in his prima precatione ad miſſa</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O holy father, receaue thou this offeringe for thy ſeruaunt whiche Moyſes receaued, when he dyd ſe in ſprite. Receaue the gifte for thy ſeruaunt, that he feruentlye deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that gifte and offering whiche the holy man, the ſtronge man, and the luſtye man doth requyre. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the oblation of thy grace for thy ſeruaunt Valyntinian nowe departed, the whiche grace he dyd neuer refuſe. <hi>Amb. in oratio funcb. ſuper obitu Valent. Imperat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thou ſhalte performe vnto me the mercy of the Lorde, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:8976:94"/> while I lyue, but euen when I am deade, and plucke not thy mercy a waye from my howſe for euer. i. Reg. i.xx.c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Of penaunce, confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſatiſfaction.</head>
            <p>YF it chaunce at any tyme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any mans hart enuye, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie, or any euell of theſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we haue ſpoken of before hathe preuilye crepte in: Let hym not be aſhamed to confeſſe theſe thinges to hym whiche ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, and taketh care and charge of the ſoule of man, that of hym and by the worde of our Lorde, and the holſome councell maye be comforte, whereby he maye auoyde with ſafe faithe, and good workes, the paynes of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall fyer, and come to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde
<pb n="lxxxviii" facs="tcp:8976:94"/> of euerlaſtynge lyfe. D. <hi>Petrus, in Epiſtola Clementis ad Iacobum fratrem domini.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We comynge by and by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, are commaunded of Saynte Clement to caſt all our euill thoughtes out of oure har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and to open them and ſhew them to the preiſtes of our Lorde. <hi>Ad Clementem in compendiolo ſuo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we reuele, open and ſhew forth our ſynnes, not onely before God, but alſo before them whiche can heale or cure oure woundes and ſynnes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſynnes ſhalbe cleane blotted oute of hym with faith. Beholde, I will put a waye your ſynnes and iniquites, euen as the cloudes whiche vanyſhe and go theyr wayes. Origen in Luke .ii. the .viii. Homil.</p>
            <p>Ther be ſome whiche do ſaye it is ſufficient for them to their
<pb facs="tcp:8976:95"/> helth and ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if they confeſſe their fawtes onelye to GOD, to whome nothinge is hyd, who kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the conſcience of menne. But they wyll not, or elſe they be aſhamed, or els diſdayne to ſhewe them ſelues to the preiſte, whome oure Lorde hath ordayned the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of the law, to diſcerne betwene leprye and leprye. But I woulde not thee to be diſceaued in that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. Foraſmuche that thou art aſhamed to be confeſſed before our Lordes vicare, conſumed through ſhame, or ſtyffenecked through diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne. For euen ſo his iudgement oughte to be obayde, whome the Lorde hath not diſdayned to ſet to be his deputie. Therefore thou ſhalte deſyre the preiſte to come to the, and make hym one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye partener of thy conſcience. <hi>Vide auguſt. De. uiſitac. infirmorum. Liber. ii.
<pb n="lxxxix" facs="tcp:8976:95"/> Cap. iiii. &amp; Lib. i. cap. ii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The remiſſion and forgeueneſſe of ſynnes by penaunce is an harde and a difficulte waye, when the ſynner doth waſhe his couche in teares. For teares are vnto hym breade bothe daye and nyght. And when he is not aſhamed to ſhew his ſynnes to the preiſt of the Lorde. <hi>Origen in leuiticum homilium. ii</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A certayne kynde of heretikes called nouatians, when they deny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preiſtes had power to bynde and looſe ſynnes, they ſayde, they deferred reuerence and honor ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of vnto the Lorde: to whome a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lone is reſerued power or auctori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of remittynge ſynnes. yea thei coulde do no greater Iniury to a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny man, then they whiche would breake the commaundement of hym: and to reſtrayne the auctori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie geuen and graunted. <hi>Ambroſ. de
<pb facs="tcp:8976:96"/> penitentia. lib. i. cap. ii.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Of prayinge to ſaynctes.</head>
            <p>ALl the ſaynctes that depart out of this life, hauinge yet charitie and loue towardes them that are in this worlde, it ſhall not be conueniente, if they be ſayde to take or execute diligent of, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute their helpe, and to ayd them with their prayers and interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before God. For it is written in the bookes of the Machabees on this wyſe: Here is Hieremye the prophet of God, which prayeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes for the people. Origen in his .iii. Homilye.</p>
            <p>O bleſſed Iob alwayes liuinge with God, and a continuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querer and veynequiſſher before oure Lord the kynge: praye for vs
<pb n="xc" facs="tcp:8976:96"/> miſerable ſynners. Origen in his ii. boke.</p>
            <p>I wyll beginne to fall vpon my knees and deſier all the ſaynctes to helpe me, that dare not my ſelfe deſire God, for the exceſſe of my ſinne: O holy ſainctes, I earneſtly pray you with teares, and weping full of ſorowe, that ye fall downe proſtrate for me miſerable ſynner before the mercy of God. <hi>Origen, in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento ſtatim abinijtio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas that euer I was borne, father Abraham intreate thou for me, that I be not put awaye from thy coſtes whiche I haue greatlye deſired, not worthelye, ſurelye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of my greate ſynne. <hi>Origen ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſublamenti finem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The innocent children ſlayne of Herode, haue the cheifeſt rowme amonge the ſainctes, and be fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liare neighbours, beynge preuye
<pb facs="tcp:8976:97"/> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyne ſecrettes, do entreate Gods clemencye for our trauelles &amp;c. And ſo they from the cradelles tranſelate into heauen, are made councellours and Iudges of the ſupernall palace, optayninge par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for ſynne not deſeruyd. &amp;c. Cypri. Ser. de ſtella, et Magi.</p>
            <p>Let vs remember one a nother that are of one harte and of one mynde, Let vs allwaye praye on bothe partes, for our ſelues, and ceaſe with mutuall loue, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixte anguyſhe, and troble of hart: and if any of vs depart fyrſt from hence with haſt as it ſhall pleaſe God let our loue contynew allway with God, let not prayer ceaſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the mercy of God the father for your brethern and ſyſters a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyue. Saynt <hi>Cypriane, i. lib. i. Epiſtle</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wolde be now in thoſe places where theſe bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of Paule other
<pb n="xci" facs="tcp:8976:97"/> are ſayde to be, &amp; wolde worſhippe worthely thoſe men whiche were of ſouche deſyer toward chriſt. I wolde deſyer to ſe thoſe chaynes whiche truely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuylles do feare &amp; tremble at, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Angelles do ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nor or worſhippe there. <hi>Ioan. chriſoſt homilium .viii. in ca. iiii. Ephe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Michaell the prince of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly warre, we vnworthy deſyre the now, that thou wilt helpe vs with thy prayers, defendynge vs vnder the ſhadow of thy wynges of thy nature that is vncorporate. We fall doune proſtrate and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute intermyſſion we call vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, delyuer vs from all perilles and daungers, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prynce of heauenly power. &amp;c. <hi>D. <hi>Ioan Chriſo. Ex miſſa.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>O mother of God all thinges are gloriouſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, ſealed with a ſecret chaſtytie, and kept in virginitie: thou arte knowne a mother with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oute
<pb facs="tcp:8976:98"/> any dyſſayte: whiche truely brought forthe our Lorde (we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche the) to praye humbly vnto hym, that he wolde ſaue our ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. Chriſo. in eadem miſſa.</p>
            <p>O mother of God for as moche as thou excelleſt all thinges that were made: we that are not able worthely to prayſe the, we beſeche the frely to haue mercy vpon vs vndeſerued. Chriſo. in eadem miſſa</p>
            <p>O father Nicholas be thou imbaſſadoure before oure Lorde Chriſt: that we maye optayne ſaluacion for our ſoules. Chriſo. in eadem miſſa.</p>
            <p>The bodyes of ſaintes, and the Relyckes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed martyrs, as the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Chriſt are to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored moſte purely, and we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, the churches dedicate to their names, ought to be gone vnto
<pb n="xcii" facs="tcp:8976:98"/> with moſte Godly affertion, and faithfull deuocion, as holy placys eſtemyd to Godly honor, if any man ſhall chaunce to be agaynſt this opinion, is not thought a Chriſten man, but to be one of the Eunominians and Vigilanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. <hi>Aug. ex eccleſiaſticorn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dogmatu. ca. lxxiii</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we will come to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of martyrs or preiſtes, let vs thinke vpon the folowynge of the martyrs, for they ought to knowe ſome thinge in vs of their vertues, that they maye vochſaue to praye to our Lorde for vs. <hi>Aug. De martiribus. Sermo. ii. et. iii</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Honor with ſobriete the byrth of ſainctes that we maye folowe them whiche wente before vs, and that they maye reioyſe of vs whiche praye for vs: that the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge of our Lorde maye alwayes contynew. So be it, and God
<pb facs="tcp:8976:99"/> grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it ſo to be. <hi>D <hi>Aug. in pſal. lxxxiiiii.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>We pray not for martyrs, but they praye for vs. <hi>D. <hi>Aug. in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uang. tracta. lxxxiiii.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>When our ſoules deſyeryth any thinge according to goddes will, and that to be geuen of God by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaintes whether they require it with the harte, tongue or voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, the ſoules of ſaintes whiche is all one for them to heare and to ſe, and contrary wiſe to ſee or to heare, beholdynge not the voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but the wordes, they optay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God for them thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that they deſyered it for. S. Auſten of knowleage of true lyfe the .xxxix. where he toucheth how the ſoules of ſayntes are vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded to here the prayers of the liuing, &amp; to help the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thexamples of iuſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore ar ſet forth, not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhulde be iuſtified of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but
<pb n="xciii" facs="tcp:8976:99"/> that we folowynge them, ſhoulde be made righteouſe alſo, of their iuſtifier. <hi>D. <hi>aug. de catechiſandus rudi. ca. 7</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>you therefore whiche haue deſerued to be made pertakers of the heauenly cytye, and to take the commoditie of the renoune of the euerlaſtynge glory, pray for me to our Lorde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he maye leade me out of this priſon in the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I am holden captyue and bounde. <hi>Auguſt. de ſpiritu et Anima. cap. lix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O all ye multitude of ſainctes intreat our lorde. O ye moſt pite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pray for vs, that we holpen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your prayers &amp; merits, maye come with a ſafe ſhepe and hole rewarde to the hauen of perpetuall health and quyetnes, and, contynew all peace and reſte, that neuer ſhall haue ende. <hi>Auguſtinus lib. meditacionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. capite xxiii</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:100"/>
            <p>Nor yet do we ordayne or erect temples, holye prieſthode, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to theſe ſame matters, not becauſe of them: but becauſe theyr God is our god. Certaynelye we honoure the memoriall of al them as holye men of God: whiche tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyled for the truth, vnto death of their bodies, that the falſe and vayne religion vanquiſſhed and ouercomed, the true holynes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygyon might be knowen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſt. de ciuitate dei. lib. viii. cap. xxiiii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The holy Aungels both dothe punyſhe them withoute wrath, whom they receaue to be punyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with eternall lawe, and alſo do helpe their miſeries withoute ſuffering or paſſion of miſery, and ayde them without feare that are in parell whome they loue. yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe they vſe alſo in thoſe, the names of theſe paſſion, be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtome
<pb n="xciiii" facs="tcp:8976:100"/> of mens ſpeaking, for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſimilitude of the dedes or actes, not for the infirmitie of the affections. As God accordinge to the ſcriptures is angry, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge is not troubled with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny paſſion. <hi>Aug. de ciuitate dei. lib. ix. cap. v</hi> Whoſoeuer be immortal &amp; bleſſed in the celeſtiall habitations, if they loue not vs, neyther wolde haue vs bleſſed. verely they are not to be honoured. But and if they loue vs, and wolde vs to be bleſſed: ſurely from thenſe woulde they haue vs vnto the place wher they are preſente. &amp;c. <hi>Aug. de ciuitate dei. Lib. x. cap. xii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What miracle ſoeuer they be, whether they be done by Angelles or any other waye, they are done by the power of God, for they ſet forthe the worſhypping and religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of one God, in whome onely
<pb facs="tcp:8976:101"/> is the bleſſed life. We muſte beleue that thoſe thinges be done indede of them, or by them whiche do loue vs according to truth and godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <hi>Aug. de ciuitate dei. Lib. x. cap. xii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For when Aungelles do heare vs, God him ſelfe doth hear vs in them, as in his true temple, &amp; not in the onely temple made with ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: like as he heareth them which do his commaundementes in this worlde amonges his ſaynctes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdynge his euerlaſtinge lawe. <hi>Auguſti. de ciuitate dei. Lib. x. cap. xii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truely he is worſe then madde whatſoeuer he be, that denieth all thinges to be in the power of the onely almighty God. <hi>Eiuſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lib. ca. xiiii</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The holy Aungelles to whoſe company and congregation we fer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uently deſire to come vnto, in this mooſt laboriouſe pylgremage, as they haue euerlaſtinge beynge, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="xcv" facs="tcp:8976:101"/> ſo haue they eaſy knowinge, &amp; fortunate reſtinge, for they helpe vs without trouble, they laboure without ſpiritual mocions for the cleane and free. <hi>Aug. de ciuitate dei. lib. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cap. xxxi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of diuers miracles which were done about the holy land, brought from Ieruſalem, and about the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of ſaint Stephen, Geruaſe Prothaſe, and other ſaynctes. Rede <hi>S. Aug. de ciuitate dei. lib. xxii. cap. viii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We do not buylde tempelles or churches to our martyrs, as vnto Gods. But we make reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce as vnto deade men, whoſe ſprites lyueth with God, neither do we ſet vp aulters in the whiche we do ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice vnto martyrs: but we do of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer both the martyrs and alſo our ſacrifice vnto one God. &amp;c. <hi>Ibidem. lib cap. x.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then without doute the holy
<pb facs="tcp:8976:102"/> martirs make interceſſion for vs, when they knowe in vs any thing of their vertues. <hi>Aug. Sermo. ccxliiii. de tempore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seinge out deſertes do burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, that we be not in the fauoure of God: let vs know that we maye be deliuered by the merites of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom God fauoreth or loueth. <hi>Aug. queſtio ſuper exodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. cap. cxlix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend our ſelues to the prayers of ſaynct Stephen, for he is greatly harde now of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtinge God, oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, for vs his oratours. &amp;c. <hi>Aug. ſermo. ii. de ſanctise</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When ye call vpon ſainctes in your prayer, ye muſte thinke thus of them, beynge conſtitute in the glorye of the euerlaſtinge cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: yf they be the moſte bryghteſt lyght ſhyninge aboue the glyſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe of the ſonne, which may haue
<pb n="xcvi" facs="tcp:8976:102"/> all good thinges, fully in the ſight of god, as well may they myghtely helpe all that call vpon them. <hi>Aug. de cognitione vere uite. ca. ix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alexander the byſhop of Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxi dyd go to Hieruſalem for the loue of worſhippinge, and ſeyng of the holy places of ſaynctes. <hi>Vide hiſt. Eccleſi. lib. vi. cap. ix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theodoſius the Emperour did lye in heere, proſtrate vppon the ground, before the tombes of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirs, and of the apoſtels, and requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red helpe or comforte to hym ſelfe with faith, and interceſſion of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Hyſto. eccleſ. xi. cap, xxxi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O holy Athanalius, loke mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifullye vpon vs, from the highe throne aboue, and directe, or defend theſe holy people. &amp;c. <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ego. Naſianſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. oratio. xviii. in Athana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A certayne Chriſtian vyrgin, moued to defyle hir virginitie of
<pb facs="tcp:8976:103"/> Cyprian, then beynge an ydolater: but ſhe callyng vpon the vyrgyn Mary, that ſhe would ſaue her vir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginite then beyng in ieopardy, her prayer was harde. <hi>Gregorie Naſiauſen. Oratio. xix. in D. Cipriano.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is an vnſemely thinge to wil to honor any holy martyr with bel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ioy, whom thou knoweſt to haue pleaſed God with faſtinge &amp; great abſtinence. <hi>D. <hi>Hyeronimus ad Euſtochium.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Paula, thy doughter Bleſill doth praye to God now for the, &amp; I know that hir mynd is ſuch that ſhe optayneth pardon for thee. <hi>D. <hi>Hyeronimus ad Paulam, ſuper obitu Bleſille.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Paula farewel, and help olde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oting age of thy ſuppliant &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipper, by thy prayers, for thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yth and thy good workes do aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ate the vnto Chriſt, &amp; thou beinge preſente with Chriſt, may farre ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyer optayne that thinge whiche
<pb n="xcvii" facs="tcp:8976:103"/> thou requireſt. <hi>D. <hi>Hieronimus in Epitaph Paule.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Of Images.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Mm"/> ANd it doth appeare in the Tripertite Hyſtory, that the ymage of Mary was had in great honour amonge the Chriſtians. <hi>liber. ix. cap. ix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Euſebius doth teſtifie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt our ſauiour, Peter, and alſo Paul was fygured of the auncient Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians, and ſaith that theſe noble tokens of aunciente men, are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be reſerued vnto the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of their poſterite, which is a true token of their honor &amp; loue <hi>Eccleſ. hiſto. lib. vii. cap. xiiii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When a certayne paynter hadde preſumed to paynte the ymage of our ſauioure, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimilitude of Iupiter, his hand was made drye: who confeſſinge his ſinnes, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:8976:104"/> man Gennadius reſtored it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. <hi>Vide hiſto. eccleſi. incephori ſub Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Imperat. pag. cccccc.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At Conſtantinople a Iewe ente<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red into the church of S. Sophy, and he conſidering y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was alone and ſaw the image of Ieſus chriſt: he toke his ſwerde and ſmote the ymage in the throte, and anone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud guſhed out, and ſprenge on the head, and on the face of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iew. He beyng afrayde, toke the image and caſt it into a pytte, and anone he fled away. And it happened that a Chriſten man met hym, and ſawe hym al bloudye, ſayd to hym, from whence comeſt thou, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt ſlayne ſome man. And he ſayde nay: And the Chriſten man ſayd: thou haſte committed ſome homiſed, for thou art all full of bloud: and the Iewe beinge aſhamed ſayde: O greate is the god of the Chriſten men, and
<pb n="cviii" facs="tcp:8976:104"/> his faith is firme, and approued in all thinges. I haue ſmitten the y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Ieſu Chriſt in the throte: and as ſone as I had ſtriken him, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud guſſhed out of his throte. And then the Iewe broughte the Chriſten man to the pitte, &amp; there drew out the holy ymage: And the wounde is yet ſene to this daye. And the Iewe became Chriſtened, and ledde an honeſte lyfe. <hi>In Hyſto. Tripert.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Abagarus kynge of the Edeſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſent a paynter to paynt an y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage like to our Lorde, the which when he could not do for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his face ſhining, our Lorde himſelf putting a cloth to his god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, &amp; liuely face, wiped of in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloth his owne ymage, &amp; ſo ſent it to the kynge Abagarus. <hi>Euſeb. Lib. i. cap. xv.</hi> This hiſtory ſheweth plainly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages do pleafe Chriſte, and not
<pb facs="tcp:8976:105"/> to be diſpleaſed with them, as he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes woulde haue it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne of the croſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Ll"/> At Alexandria, euerye man had the ſigne of the croſſe paynted v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their poſtes, and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> entringe to of their houſes, and pillers. <hi>Eccleſ. hyſt. lib. xi. ca. xxix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Iulyanus thapoſtita, bleſſinge him ſelfe with the ſigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe draue away the deuill, thoughe it were againſt his will. <hi>Eccl. hyſt. lib. vi. cap. ix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecretes of the chriſtians hath a certaine worthye reuerente token, the whiche token or ſigne they name the croſſe, by the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the croſſe it ſelf: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which both in dede, we affyrme moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy of honour: and alſo we worſhip it for the remembraunce of hym
<pb n="lxcix" facs="tcp:8976:105"/> that was crucified theron. <hi>Aug. de ui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitatione infirmorum. lib. ii. cap. iii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The croſſe is geuen to vs vpon our head, and that it is a ſhielde, a buckeler, and a cote of armoure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the deuyl. There this ſigne muſt be worſhipped of vs, geuinge the honour and reuerence to god. They that do worſhip rhis figure of the croſſe, let them be (o Lorde) partakers of Chriſt crucified, <hi>Dama<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſene. lib. iiii. cap. xxii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the ſigne of the Croſſe, all wichcraft, or ſorcery, and the act or craft of poyſoning, is put away, yf it be done in faith and deuotion. <hi>Athanaſius. lib. de incar. uer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is redde in the <hi>Hyſtoria Scolaſtica</hi> that the paynims had paynted on a wall the armes of one Serapis. And Theodoſien the Emperoure dyd put out the ſayde armes, and paynted in the ſame place y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne
<pb facs="tcp:8976:106"/> of the croſſe. And when the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyms of the prieſtes of the ydolles ſawe the ſigne of the croſſe pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there, anone they became chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened, ſaying: that they learned of their elders, that thoſe armes ſhould ſtand, vntyll ſuche a ſigne were ſet there, where in ſhalbe ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            <p>S. Chriſoſtome ſayth, that the croſſe and the woundes of Chriſt: ſhall geue more lyght at the daye of iudgement, then the ſonne.</p>
            <p>The deuils ſeinge Moſes lawe feared not, nor trembled not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath not wrought mans health, but ſeynge the croſſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che Chriſte dyed vppon, they ofte quake, flee, and vanyſhe awaye. Of the whiche it fyrſte came, that meate, drinke, and all other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are bleſſed with the ſigne of the croſſe. Athanaſ. xxiviii. queſt.</p>
            <pb n="c" facs="tcp:8976:106"/>
            <p>When in Ieruſalem the Iewes were almoſt all ſlayne with a rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thinge of fyre lyke a boule, and the reſt for feare of death, were enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and conſtrayned to confeſſe Chriſt Ieſu to be God: leaſte that thinge ſhould haue ben thoughte to haue happened by chaunce, the nighte folowinge the ſigne of the croſſe dyd ſo euidently appeare in all their garments, that he, which for his vnfaithfulnes would haue taken it awaye, coulde not in no wiſe. Therefore let men beware y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> do diſpiſe the picture of the croſſe, or the crucifixes of Chriſt, leſt lyke vengeaunce of God do light vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. Tripert. hiſtory.</p>
            <p>The good &amp; godly emperoure Conſtantine, when he was turned to chriſtes faith, &amp; hard much prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching of the croſſe, when he was in warfare, he commaunded cunning
<pb facs="tcp:8976:107"/> men to chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge his baner y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had into a baner of the croſſe made of gold, and precious ſtones. For chis ſigne of warre was among others more precious, or eſtemed better, becauſe it wente before the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure, and the cuſtome was of the ſouldiers to worſhippe it. <hi>Hyſto. Tri pert. lib. i. cap. v.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The emperour Conſtantine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many &amp; diuers notable victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, optayned of his enemies, accu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtoming his ſouldiers to honoure God, as he did him ſelfe, he made their armoure to haue the ſigne of the croſſe: he did moſt honoure the holy croſſe (as the Hiſtorye ſayth) both for the good lucke whiche he had in warre by the helpe of it, and for the ſigne whiche God ſhewed therby. <hi>Trip. Hyſto. lib. i. cap. ix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whan this emperoure Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine was in great care &amp; thought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="ci" facs="tcp:8976:107"/> how he ſhould optayne victory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte his ennemies, he ſawe in a dreame y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appearing in the firmament, &amp; the aungels ſtanding by hym, wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering at the ſigne, ſaying: <hi>O <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine in hoc uince.</hi>
               </hi> That is to ſaye. O Conſtantyne, thou ſhalt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thy enemies, by this ſigne of the croſſe.</p>
            <p>Sozomenus writ this aboue .xii c. yeares agoo. And it is alſo (ſaith the ſtory Treportide) that Chriſte apeared vnto him, and ſhewed him a ſigne of the croſſe, commaunding him to make a lyke figure, &amp; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, that ſhalbe thy helpe in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, wherby thou ſhalt get the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorye.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Of the counſels &amp; aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rities of the fathers.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:108"/>
            <p>TRuly I would not beleue the goſpell, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les the auctorities of the churche had moued me ther vnto: vnto whom I haue ben obe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dient ſayinge: beleue the goſpell. Wherfore ſhould I not beleue the church ſaying: beleue not the Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niches, <hi>Aug. contra epiſtolam Manichei, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fundamenti uocant. cap. v.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in myne olde age I wyll kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith that I was broughte vp withall, <hi>Hyeronimus ad occanum et pammacheum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is my parte to reade the olde fathers, and ſingularlye to holde and alow al thinges that be good, and not to degreſſe from the fayth of the catholyke churche. <hi>D. Hieroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ad Mineruum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ought to learne the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege of the ſcriptures, of hym whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath kept it from our auncient fathers after the truthe geuen
<pb n="cii" facs="tcp:8976:108"/> vnto hym. And he maye affirme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petently thoſe thinges whiche he hath rightfully receaued. <hi>Clemens epi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſto. iiii. ad eccleſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hieroſoli.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. Clement Paules companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in preaching the golpell, affirme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h that ſ. Peter thapoſtel did teache that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to obey the biſhops commaundementes in all lawfull thinges, thoughe they dyd other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe lyue, hearing in remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce our Lordes precepte ſayinge: Do ye the thinges whiche they ſay or bydde you do, but do you not as they do, for they ſaye and do not. Alſo he ſayeth: oure hartes and bodyes muſte be prepared vnto the holye obedyence of Goddes commaundementes, and hys byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes and preachers: that we maye eſcape the payne of Hell, and come to euerlaſtynge glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye. In hys fyrſte Epyſtell
<pb facs="tcp:8976:109"/> wrytten to ſaynct Iames. And fat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther he ſaith in the ſame epiſtle: let no man beleue that theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes are to be deſpiſed, or diſſembled without his peryll, becauſe that he ſhal ſuffer by gods iudgement the paynes of fire euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſtinge, which ſhall deſpiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches decrees, or determinations.</p>
            <p>Theſe thinges S. Clement lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of S. Peters owne mouth.</p>
            <p>We haue receaued the rightes whiche are obſerued and preached in the church, part therof we haue receaued by writinge, part by the traditions of the Apoſtels, whiche both hath like ſtrength vnto ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and no manne hath ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this whiche at the laſt hath had but a little experience of the eccleſiaſticall lawe. For if we take in hande to diſpiſe olde cuſtomes not brought forth by writinge, as
<pb n="ciii" facs="tcp:8976:109"/> hauing litle ſtrength: Trulye we lyke vnwiſe men do infourme, and bringe in daunger vnto the moſte cheifeſt fathers, nay rather we do drawe the very preachinge of the goſpell to an euyll name, or a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked reporte. &amp;c. <hi>Aug. ad emeritum contra Donatiſtas. Epiſto. C.lxiiii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the councels them ſelues that be done in euery priuate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion or prouince, oughte to geue place without any doubte, to the auctoritie of the general councels, whiche is done throughe all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, and al thinges that was done before to be amended to oure poſterities, by ſome experience of thinges, the thinge is open which before was ſhut. And that is kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen which was hid withoute anye figure or proud ſacrilege. And w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the puffed vp necke of arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, and without the contencion of
<pb facs="tcp:8976:110"/> the yrefull malice, with holy humi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litie, catholike peace, and chriſtien charitie. <hi>Aug de baptiſmo, contra donatiſtas. lib. ii. cap. ii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like maner as the littell bees dothe ſit vpon the flowers and herbes, with their lyttell feate &amp; light winges, and doth carye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye the hydden Iuyce without any hurre to the floure, that at the lengthe they maye miniſter vnto men the ſwete hony combes made in their lyttell holes: Euen ſo the doctors of the churche are ſytting aboute the pleſaunte and grene bourgenynge of ſcripture, with a light wynge of mynde: And are very diligent drawing the Iuyce of the holy goſte, of the hyd letter, that they maye inſtill the moſte ſwete hony of faithe into the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the auditors. <hi>Chri. in pſal cxv.</hi>
               <pb n="ciiii" facs="tcp:8976:110"/> I do confeſſe my ſelf ſaid S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorye, to receaue and reuerence y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iiii. cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels euen as the .iiii. euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſtes. S. Gregorie vppon the counſel of Nece, and of the .iiii. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther counſels.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vincentius Lyrmencis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> anno. ccc.l.</head>
               <p>If any man ſhall aſke me, what nede is it to folowe the auctoritie of Chriſtes churche, and here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandinge of ſcriptures, ſeinge the ſcriptures is perfight of it ſelf and ſufficient. I aunſwer to hym, that we muſt nedes ſo do, becauſe all men do not expound the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in one ſence. But euery man after his owne wytte and fantaſy. And ſo therby there ſhoulde aryſe moche diſſencion debate, ſtrife, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and many hereſies ſprynge vp and be defended in Chriſtes churche except her expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld be admitted. Eſay. vii. b</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8976:111"/>
               <p>If ye beleue not, it commeth of this, that ye are vnfaithfull vnto God. yea truelye, for the vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes that man will not geue cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dite vnto his wordes. He therefore toke away the intelligence of man that he ſhall not perceiue the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of his works, &amp; ſo ſuffred him to ronne headling into deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>¶ Agaynſt the mariage of preiſtes</head>
            <p>THoſe that do vowe their vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginite vnto God, albeit thei receaue an hyer degre of honor &amp; ſanctifie or holynes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche, neuertheleſſe thei are not without matrimoni, for thei do alſo ꝑtayne in matrimonye with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche Chriſt is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpouſe. <hi>Aug tractatu. ix. in Euange. Ioh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the churche is called a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin,
<pb n="cv" facs="tcp:8976:111"/> ther be dyuers members of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche, for they do ſhyne with dyuers gyftes. For there be ſome men maried, and ſome women ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, ſome men viduate from their wiues, and ſome women be alſo vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duate from their huſbandes, and after that ſeke not for mariage, ſome do conſerue and kepe theyr virginitie, euen from their youth, and other of maydens and wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n do vowe their virginitie vnto God. <hi>Aug. tracta. iii. in euang. Ioh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A vowe once made by virgins or wydowes (nowe not only to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but alſo if they were not mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) to wyll to mary, is damnable. For as the Apoſtle dydde declare this thing, he ſayd not, when they did liue in pleaſures they marrye in Chriſt: but he ſayde: when they wyll to marye, they haue damnati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on on their headdes, becauſe they
<pb facs="tcp:8976:112"/> haue made their fyrſt faithe voyde not onely in mariage, but in wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge to mary: not becauſe the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of ſuch are Iudged to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempned, but the diſſayte of their purpoſe is condempned, and alſo the brekinge of their wowe is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempned. Mariage whiche is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer goodnes is not condempned: But the vowe vnto God whiche is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higher goodnes is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempned, To be ſhort, all ſuche are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, not becauſe they do bringe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeconde matrimony: but becauſe they haue broken or made voyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt faithe of their contynency. Farthermore, thoſe whiche do ſaye that the mariage of ſouche is no mariage, but rather aduoutrie: they do apeare to me not to ſpeak ſharpelye ynoughe, nor doth not diligently conſider what thei may ſpeake therof &amp;c. <hi>Aug: de bona uiduitati <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="cvii" facs="tcp:8976:112"/> bide to receaue chriſtes bodye whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is greater then prayer? if he forbere not hys wyues company for a tyme. If a lay man ſhall for beare the company of his laufull wyfe: moche more a preiſt to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye. <hi>Iheronimus in apologia ad Iouinianum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If lay men be commaunded that they ſhoulde abſtayne the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their wyues for prayer ſake, what is it to be thought of a byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe or a preiſt, whiche ſhoulde offer cleane ſacrifice vnto God for them ſelues and the ſynnes of the people. Ierome in Tite.</p>
            <p>They are not to be harde whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che dothe fayne that Paule had a wyfe, when he diſputinge of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and parſwadinge men to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the contynuall gyfte of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtytie, for I wold (ſaith he), that al men ſhold be, as I am. <hi>hiero ad Euſto.</hi> All the Apoſtles except Iohn and
<pb facs="tcp:8976:113"/> Paule had wiues. <hi>Ambro. in. ii. Cor. xi</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is better to mary then to burne. This ſayinge of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtel doth not belonge to a woman that hath hyr faithe, nor yet with her whiche hathe not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vaele, But whoſoeuer hathe promiſid them ſelfe to Chriſt and hathe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued the holye vaele, is imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diattlye maryed vnto Chriſte, and forth with maryed vnto an immortall huſbande. If ſhe after this, will be maryed by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law of wedloke, ſhe lyueth in adultry, and is made the childe of deathe. <hi>D. <hi>Ambro. ad virginem lapſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cap. v.</hi>
               </hi> S. Paul ſayd not (ſayth. S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome) let hym be choſen a byſhop that mariethe a wyfe, and be get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tethe chylder, but he that hath but one wyfe, and chylder brought vp in all good order and diſciplyne. And this ye confeſſe yourſelfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb n="cviii" facs="tcp:8976:113"/> no man can be a byſhoppe that be getteth chyldern after he is made a byſhop. For if he be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue ſo done, he ſhall not be counted as a laufull huſband, but condemned for a veri aduoutrer. <hi>S. <hi>hiero. lib. i. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Iouinianum.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>A preiſt if he do mary, ought to be degraded, if he commyte forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or aduoutry, he ought to be caſt out of the churche, and be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to penaunce amonges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laite. <hi>Conſilium Neoceſnenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We vtterly forbyde (ſayth S. Clement) preiſtes, deacons, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, and monkes to kepe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubynes, or to contract mariage.</p>
            <p>He only (ſayth Origen) may of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the continuall and euerlaſting ſacrifice, which maketh a vow of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall &amp; euerlaſtyng continencie Orig. againſt preiſtes mariages.</p>
            <p>We do vtterly forbyd preiſtes
<pb facs="tcp:8976:114"/> deacons, ſubdeacons, and monkes to haue concubynes or marye: for all ſuche mariages ſhalbe found vnlaufull, and the parties dryuen to do open penaunce. Calixius y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy man. Aboue all thynges the preiſt whiche is aſſiſtant at the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of God, ought to be garniſhed with chaſtitie <hi>Orig. in leuiti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Suſan (ſayth. S. Ierome) for gettyng this holy purpoſe, whych had bounde thee to chaſtitie, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gettinge thy parentes, the holy church, the glory of virginitie, the honor of that high dignitie, the promiſſe of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the terrible day of Iudgement, thou haſt catched in thyne armes corruption, thou haſt brought forth the fruit of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and at the end a moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll and paynefull deathe euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge, <hi>hiero. lxxiii. epiſto. ad ruſticum.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="list_of_authors">
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:114"/>
            <head>¶ The auctors contained in this boke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Anacletus,</item>
               <item>Alexander</item>
               <item>Ambroſe</item>
               <item>Auguſtine</item>
               <item>Aucelme</item>
               <item>Athanaſius</item>
               <item>Baſyll</item>
               <item>Barnard</item>
               <item>Bruno</item>
               <item>Clement</item>
               <item>Chriſoſtome</item>
               <item>Ciprian</item>
               <item>Cirill</item>
               <item>Catho.</item>
               <item>Deonyſe</item>
               <item>Damaſon</item>
               <item>Damaſus</item>
               <item>Euſebius</item>
               <item>Eraſmus</item>
               <item>Felyxmartir</item>
               <item>Gregori Emiſſen</item>
               <item>Gerſon</item>
               <item>Haymo</item>
               <item>Hyllary</item>
               <item>Hierom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Hugo</item>
               <item>Ignatius</item>
               <item>Ireneus</item>
               <item>Leo papa</item>
               <item>Luther</item>
               <item>Marciall</item>
               <item>Melancton</item>
               <item>Nicolaus de Lyra</item>
               <item>Origen</item>
               <item>Oecumenius</item>
               <item>Petrus Lumbardus</item>
               <item>Rupertus</item>
               <item>Rabanus</item>
               <item>Sedulius</item>
               <item>Tertullian</item>
               <item>Theophilactus</item>
               <item>The Kynges boke of com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon prayer</item>
               <item>The counſel of Loterane</item>
               <item>The determination of the hole Vniuerſitie of Pari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:115"/>
            <head>¶ A table of the principal matters contayned in the boke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>A. Of breade is made the fleſh, or bodye of Chriſt. fol. 10 11 12 21 24 25 31 46 61 63 71 73.</item>
               <item>B Bread and wyne is turned, chaunged, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conuerted into the body and bloud of chriſt Fol. 12 13 25 43 44 61 63 66 69 71 72 73.</item>
               <item>C Of wyne and water is made the bloud that redemed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people. Fol, 9 24 25 63 65 66</item>
               <item>D Bread doth appeare, but it is fleſh. 61.</item>
               <item>E Of the royall preſens of Chriſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and of his corporall eatyng. fol. 72 73 74 75 76.</item>
               <item>F We eate the ſame fleſhe that was borne of the virgin, and walked here in earth. Fol. 26. 27. 32. 50. 74.</item>
               <item>G Chriſt ſitteth on the right hande of the father, &amp; yet at the tyme of ſacrifice, he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayned in the handes of men, and geuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. fol 15 19.</item>
               <item>H Chriſt hath not only taken his fleſh vp with him into heauen, but alſo hath lefte it with vs here in earth. Fol, 19.</item>
               <item>I After conſecration it is not called bread and wyne, but the body and bloud of chriſte Fol. 21 56 79</item>
               <item>K Chriſt was hole with the father when he came into the vyrgin and fylled her, and hole in euery parte of the hoſt being broken Fol. 40</item>
               <item>L The body of Chriſt is both the figure, &amp; the veritie. Fol. 34 6 15 63 67.</item>
               <item>M How the body of Chriſt that honge on the croſſe, is receaued inuiſibly, and not vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiblye. Fol. 42.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:8976:115"/>
               <item>N We offer on the aulter, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body &amp; bloud of Chriſt, to optayne euerlaſtinge lyfe. Fol, 8 37 57 58</item>
               <item>O In the ſacrament of the aulter is remiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of ſynnes. fol. 25. 49 74.</item>
               <item>P There is but one ſacrifice, &amp; one Chriſt offered, though it be done in neuer ſo many places at once. Fol. 15 16 19 35 48.</item>
               <item>Q Chriſt was borne in his owne handes. Fol 31 29 34.</item>
               <item>R If Chriſt had not ben meke, he woulde nether haue ben eaten, nor yet dronken. Fol, 34 41</item>
               <item>S In the bread and wine which we do ſe, we do honour and worſhip, that we do not ſe, fleſhe and bloud. Fol. 15 21 29 32 33 43 67 68 70.</item>
               <item>T There is as muche difference betwene the ſhew breades and the body of Chriſt, as is betwene a ſhadow and a body. Fol 47</item>
               <item>V The preiſt doth not make the body and bloud of Chriſt, but it is Chriſte that was crucified for vs. 7 8 19 21 44 46 47 71 72 73</item>
               <item>X The Euchariſt is the fleſhe, bodye and bloud of Chriſt. Fol 0 10 13</item>
               <item>Y Chriſt gaue to his diſciples that, that he was him ſelfe, that was his owne bodye Fol. 15 13 18 33 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 46</item>
               <item>z There be to maners of the eating of our Lorde. fol 44</item>
               <item>&amp; The holy porcion paſſeth not throughe the body (as heretikes woulde haue it) lyke other meates, Fol, 63 68 71</item>
               <item>Aa At the time of ſacrifice the deſcription of ſainctes is preſent, Fol 78 80</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:8976:116"/>
               <item>Bb In olde tyme all that were within the church degrees did receaue, Fol. 2, 6.</item>
               <item>Cc In olde tyme they that were baptiſed, receaued the body of our lorde. Fol, 2 6</item>
               <item>Dd It is not lawfull to do ſacrifice or maſſe in euery place, Fol 1 4</item>
               <item>Ee Inuocation vpon the bread and wine vſed at maſſe, both by S, Clement, and alſo by S, Ambroſe. Fol 5 24 27</item>
               <item>Ff The goſpell is not to be beleued, but by the churche, Fol, 11, 44, 75</item>
               <item>Gg Of almoſe, and faſtinge. Fol, 41</item>
               <item>Hh Of confeſſion, penaunce, and ſatiſfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Fol 42 87</item>
               <item>Ii Of inuocation and praying vnto ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes, Fol <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9</item>
               <item>Kk Of the councels and of the auctorities of the fathers of Chriſtes church, fol 76 For the dead, Fol 73</item>
               <item>Ll Of the croſſe, Fol 63 67 98</item>
               <item>Mm Of ymages, Fol 97</item>
               <item>Nn Againſt the mariage of preiſtes, fo. 46</item>
               <item>Oo The ſacramentes are committed to, iii degrees, fol 3</item>
               <item>Pp Of the fragmentes of our lordes body and place of reſeruation, Fol, 3 4</item>
               <item>Qq The cheifeſt office belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging to a preiſt is to miniſter the Euchariſt. fol, 6</item>
               <item>Rr, Preiſtes are to be honored, for they haue power both to miniſter, &amp; alſo to bind &amp; loſe in earth, &amp; ſo hath nether angels, arch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>angels, nor poteſtates, Fol, 14. 20</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don in Alderſgate ſtrete by William Harford, for Wylliam Seres. <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8976:116"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
